<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Backgrounders xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
	<Term Title="About Balance of the Planet">
		<Text><![CDATA[<p style="font-size:110%">I want to make this game a lot better. I want to have better images. I want more links to references and resources. I want more background pages. I want to make it available for free on the Web, so that people can play it with a browser.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">There is also a major improvement that I had originally planned that wasn't implemented in this version of the game. The biggest weakness of this game is that the calculations involve assumptions that different people will find objectionable. For example, how safe is nuclear power? There's a number in the game for that, but is the number too big or too small? Some people will say that it's too big; some will say that it's too small. Who's right?</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">In this game, I had to up with the best number I could based on my research. But I want to link each page to a special "formula page" that allows the player to adjust the numbers that control the equations. That way, you could decide for yourself exactly how safe nuclear power is, how cheap or expensive solar power is, how fast climate change is proceeding, how important economic growth is, and so on. This would immensely improve the game. All the basic data structures are in place to make this happen, but I had to leave them unused for now.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">Another idea that I'd like to do is the provision of "biased versions" of the game. One version would use a set of numbers reflecting what an environmentalist might prefer; another version would present what a businessman might prefer.</p>		
		<p style="font-size:110%">If you know somebody who'd like to fund a proper version of this game, have them contact me at balance@erasmatazz.com</p>
		]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[<a href="http://www.erasmatazz.com/library/design-diaries/design-diary-balance-of-the/index.html">my series of design essays about this game</a>]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="Absorption">
		<Text><![CDATA[<p style="font-size:110%">Molecules can ring like bells; every molecule has some basic frequencies that it resonates at. Their ringing frequences are much higher than bells. Many molecules have resonance frequencies that are in the same general ballpark as the frequencies that photons have.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">Each photon has a color, and that color corresponds to a specific frequency (see the backgrounder on <a href="Light">light</a>).</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">Let's just suppose that we've got an innocent little photon flying through the atmosphere and it hits a molecule. If the molecule's natural frequency doesn't match the photon's frequency, nothing happens, and the photon flies right by as if the molecule wasn't there.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">But if the molecule's natural frequency just happens to be close to the photon's frequency, then the molecule absorbs the photon. It gobbles up the photon and starts ringing at its frequency.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">Molecules aren't exactly like bells: a molecule's ringing doesn't fade away naturally. Instead, after ringing for a tiny fraction of a second, the molecule changes its mind and disgorges the photon.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">But there's a catch: the direction that it vomits out the photon at is NOT the same as the direction the photon was originally going; in effect, the molecule changes the course of the photon in a random way. The fact that it vomits out the photon in a random new direction is critical to the next step: <a href="Greenhouse%20Effect">the greenhouse effect</a>.</p>]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="Anti-Nukes">
		<Text><![CDATA[
		<p style="font-size:110%">Nuclear power is a complicated and difficult subject. But to some people – the <i>anti-nukes</i> – it's really quite simple: nuclear power is evil and dangerous. These people are mucking up the important public debate with irrational emotionalism.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">Don't get me wrong: there is a respectable case against nuclear power. There are some very well-informed people who oppose nuclear power. But I have studied the subject for many years and my opinion is that the preponderance of evidence favors nuclear power, and the dangers of nuclear power are much overrated. I respect those well-informed people with whom I disagree – but I do disagree with them. Here are three bad reasons why some people oppose nuclear power:</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%"><b>Irrational fear of radioactivity:</b> It is certainly understandable that people would fear the unknown, and few people have ever had the chance to familiarize themselves with the effects of radioactivity. Yes, radioactivity can definitely be dangerous: but so can electricity, automobiles, and household chemicals. In fact, each of these dangers kills many more people every year than radioactivity kills. But you aren't afraid of electricity, cars, or household chemicals, because you use them every day. You respect the dangers they impose, but you don't fear them. In the same way, a reasonable person should assess the dangers of radioactivity the same way that they might assess the dangers of electricity, cars, or household chemicals. A calm, rational assessment of the risks shows that the fearmongering of many anti-nukes is just wrong.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%"><b>It's Big Business:</b> Most of us have a healthy skepticism about the motives of big corporations. We're also pretty wary of Big Government, and Big Science doesn't warm the cockles of our hearts, either. And where do Big Business, Big Government, and Big Science come together? Right: in nuclear power plants. So all of our healthy, natural wariness is set on high alert when we consider nuclear power. There's nothing wrong with being skeptical about nuclear power – but skepticism is not the same thing as opposition. I encourage you to learn everything you can about nuclear power. Not just lots of anti-nuclear stuff, nor lots of pro-nuclear stuff. Read stuff from <u>both</u> sides so that you can make an independent decision. I list some links below (and in other places in this game) to help you find both sides of the issues.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%"><b>It's what my friends believe:</b> If you run around with a liberal crowd, you're probably opposed to nuclear power; if you run around with a conservative crowd, you're probably in favor of nuclear power. Don't you think that's kind of silly? I mean, what does your political preference have to do with the complicated technical issues of nuclear power? If you really want to be a good citizen, don't just follow the crowd: find out for yourself and make your own decisions based on the evidence you uncover. And don't get all your evidence from just one side: whatever your biases, make sure to carefully read a broad spectrum of sources.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">If you do study the issue carefully, you'll learn that it's a complicated subject and it's easy to mislead people by telling only part of the story. Radioactive waste disposal is <b>not</b> a technical problem: we know how to do it safely. But it <b>is</b> a huge political problem. Given the fact that people are so jumpy about radioactivity, how can you dump all the radioactive waste from all over the country in just one place?</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">It shouldn't take you long to learn that nuclear power plants cannot explode like atom bombs; that's impossible, period. However, if they overheat, they can build up a bubble of hydrogen gas, and the hydrogen gas <b>can</b> explode. In fact, that happened <b>three times</b> at <a href="What Happened at Fukushima">Fukushima</a>. </p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">Some people argue that nuclear power plants are so expensive that they don't make economic sense. That's only true when we saddle them with endless lawsuits that delay construction. If we just set clear regulations and let people get on with it, nuclear power plants would be cost-effective. They're not cheap, but they are still worthwhile. And yes, as people learn more about the technology, we can reduce some of the costs.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">There is one argument against nuclear power that has some real substance. Nuclear power plants are like airplanes: operated properly, they're extremely safe. But it has taken us almost a hundred years to learn enough about airplanes to build up an entire community of pilots, mechanics, air traffic controllers, and lots of other people who are all exquisitely sensitive to safety. We have not had as much time learning about nuclear power plant operations. If everybody working at nuclear power plants were as well trained and as well paid as the people who keep airplanes flying, nuclear power plants would be just as safe as airplanes. But are they all, each and every one, really that good?</p>
		]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[
		<a href="http://www.nirs.org/">Nuclear Information Resource Center</a><br/>
		<a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/usa/en/">Greenpeace</a><br/>
		<a href="http://www.sierraclub.org/nuclear/">The Sierra Club</a><br/>
		
		<a href="http://www.ecolo.org/base/baseen.htm">Environmentalists for Nuclear Power</a><br/>
		<a href="http://casenergy.org/">Clean and Safe Nuclear Energy</a><br/><br/>
		
		Some old classics:<br/>
		<a href="http://www.stephankinsella.com/wp-content/uploads/texts/beckmann_health-hazards-not-going-nuclear.pdf">The Health Hazards of Not Going Nuclear</a> This is a cranky but hilarious attack on anti-nuclear ideology. The author plays a bit fast and loose with the facts, but he's close enough to the truth to score some solid hits.<br/>
		<a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0060906537/ref=cm_cr_asin_lnk">Soft Energy Paths, by Amory Lovins.</a> This book is not specifically about nuclear power, but it is a classic because it approached our energy problems from a fresh angle. It is certainly thought-provoking, even though it is 40 years old. Some of Mr. Lovin's optimistic predictions were not borne out, and so his conclusions aren't substantiated, but his approach is illuminating and deserves consideration by everybody.<br/>
		]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="Automobile Safety">
		<Text><![CDATA[<p style="font-size:110%">Most people think that big cars are safer than small cars. There is some truth in this statement – but not much. The weight of a car is a minor factor in overall automotive safety.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">Suppose that you're in a big car and you crash into a concrete abutment. That abutment isn't going to yield an inch. So what do you need for protection?</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">Let's compare two imaginary cars colliding with a solid concrete abutment. Both cars have the engine in the rear of the car. One car has five feet of solid steel armor plate in front of the driver; the other car has absolutely nothing in front of the driver. Which driver is safer?<p>
<p style="font-size:110%">Surprise, surprise, the answer is that they're both equally at risk. Why? Because the concrete is solid, and so when the car hits the concrete, it must stop in an instant. If you're the driver without any protection, your body crashes into the concrete at full speed. But if you're the driver with the huge armor plate, it's no different: your body still crashes at full speed, but this time it crashes into the armor plate instead of the concrete. It makes no difference whether you crash at 60 mph into solid concrete or solid steel: you're still squooshed.<p>
<p style="font-size:110%">What you need is not solid dead weight but cushioning. That's what the air bag is for, but it can provide only so much cushioning. What you really want is a front end that crumples up nicely in a collision. Look closely at the photograph: notice how the front end of the car is crumpling up neatly. All the energy that was in the moving car is being used to crumple all that metal. The whole front end is designed so that the maximum amount of metal must be bent in order for the front end to crumple. All that metal-bending absorbs lots of energy – energy that does NOT go into ripping apart your body. By contrast, steel armor plate doesn't absorb any energy – it just transmits it straight to your body.<p>
<p style="font-size:110%">The same thing goes if you hit a concrete abutment, a big tree, a telephone pole, or any other stationary object. Unless it gives way, you want lots of crumply cushioning. And it's just as important for sideways collisions or rear-end collisions.<p>
<p style="font-size:110%">There is one situation where having extra weight enhances your safety. If you crash head-on into another car, then if your car is heavier than the other guy's car, you'll be safer than the other guy. That's because the extra weight of your car forces his car to stop more quickly than your car, so his car must absorb more energy more quickly than your car. But there's a catch (there's ALWAYS a catch!): your greater safety is gained by making everybody else less safe. Because your car is heavier than other people's cars, any collision with your car has more destructive energy than a collision with a regular-size car. In other words, you're making the roads more dangerous for everybody else in order to make the roads safer for yourself. Isn't that selfish?<p>
<p style="font-size:110%">Remember also that big cars aren't as nimble as smaller cars, so it's easier to get into an accident in the first place with a big car. And of course, the most important factor in automobile safety is you, the driver. Being a careful driver will do far more to insure your safety than having a big car.<p>
<p style="font-size:110%">Adding it all up, the safety advantage of a big heavy car is pretty small.<p>]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[<a href="http://www.safercar.gov/Safety+Ratings">safety ratings for different cars</a><br>
		<a href="http://www.census.gov/compendia/statab/cats/transportation/motor_vehicle_accidents_and_fatalities.html">statistics on car accidents</a><br><br><br><br><br><br><br>	
		<a href="http://theinspirationroom.com/daily/print/2008/10/mercedes_crash_test_mammogram.jpg">crash image</a><br/>]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="Bagger 288">
		<Text><![CDATA[<p style="font-size:110%">This is the largest land vehicle on the planet, and it gets the worst mileage of anything! It is the Bagger 288, built in Germany to excavate huge seams of coal several hundred feet below ground. It simply eats through the dirt above the coal, exposing the coal. Then it collects the coal.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">This is one big machine! It is 800 feet long and 300 feet high, weighs 13,000 tons, and boasts a top speed of nearly 0.4 mph. It is powered by electricity, requiring some 16 megawatts of power, which is about 20,000 horsepower. This translates into approximately 1,300 gallons of gasoline per mile, or about 0.0007 mpg.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">The first Bagger 288 was built in 1979. The machine is typically used at a mine site for a number of years and then will move, under its own power, to a nearby mine site. This is a rather complicated process; it takes three weeks to move 10 miles. Along the way, they have to use bulldozers to prepare a level, smooth path for it. Where it crosses roads, they build a huge dirt "overpass" for the Bagger 288 to move over.. The trip costs $8 million, which is still cheaper than disassembling the machine, transporting the parts, and rebuilding it.<p>
<p style="font-size:110%">The manufacturer, Krupp, is now working on the Bagger 288z, a sporty version which will be available in Sapphire Blue, Firetruck Crimson, and Eco-Green. Racing stripes are optional. There were plans to organize a Gran Prix for competing Bagger 288s in the city of Monaco, but the city fathers, not wishing to see their city squashed, squashed the idea.<p>]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[
		<a href="http://www.knowtheauto.com/2012/09/bagger-288-monster-or-machine.html">an article about the Bagger 288</a><br>
		<a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=wUzYIg7u_c4">video of the Bagger 288 in action</a><br>
		<a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=wO3thZwQxUU&feature=endscreen&NR=1">what happens when a bulldozer tangles with a Bagger</a><br><br><br><br><br><br><br><br>
				
		<a href="http://www.oto6.fr/6roues/atv/bagger2881.jpg">Bagger image</a><br/>]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="Behavioral Energy Conservation">
		<Text><![CDATA[<p style="font-size:110%">Energy conservation is not just a matter of new and better technology. One of the simplest and easiest ways to conserve energy is simply not to waste it! Americans waste enormous amounts of energy. Here are some of the things that you can do to reduce energy waste:<br><b>Turn the lights off when they're not needed.</b> Some people just never remember to turn off the lights when they leave a room. A small room takes about one cent's worth of electricity to keep lighted for one hour. As time goes on, that cost will increase. It only takes a second to turn off the lights. It's just a matter of making a habit out of it.<br><b>Don't keep the house so warm in the winter</b> This wastes enormous amounts of energy. Lots of Americans keep their houses at 72º in the winter. That's ridiculous. Europeans keep their houses much colder, and I myself keep my house at about 58º during the winter, saving enormous amounts of energy. I am especially sensitive to the cold, but I just wear long johns,  heavy undershirts, a sweater, and two pairs of socks. If we're going to watch TV, my wife and I will sometimes use a little throw blanket that we keep by the couch. We also have covers for the windows to insure that we don't lose too much heat out the windows. Our house is big, and we live in the mountains where it gets pretty cold, and we have to use electricity for heating, but our monthly heating bill is only a $400 per month. This is about half what it cost the previous owners of the house.<br><b>Don't keep the house so cold in the summer.</b> Hey, I hate  sweltering temperatures just as much as the next guy, and I'm not about to suffer. We have house-wide air conditioning, but we seldom use it. In the first place, our house is surrounded by tall trees that block out much of the sunlight; that really keeps the place cool. Also, we cool ONLY the parts of the house we're actually using: my office during the day (it's upstairs where all the heat collects, and the computer equipment heats up the office); and the main bedroom for about an hour before bedtime. We open up the house at night when it's cool outside, and we even have window fans to push the hot air out of the top of the house, drawing cool air in through the lower windows. When morning comes, we button everything back up and the house stays cool throughout most of the day. If your house has an attic, an attic fan that automatically turns on when it gets hot will get you a lot more cooling per kilowatt-hour than an air conditioner will.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">But easily the biggest way to save energy (and money!) is to <b>cut down transportation costs</b>. Assuming that you drive about 12,500 miles per year (a typical number for Americans), then you will spend approximately $6,000 per year on a small car and $10,000 per year on a large car or SUV. That means that buying the smaller car will save you $4,000 per year.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">Another easy way to save money and energy is to <b>drive less</b>. There are lots of errands that need not be run today – put them off until you can consolidate them all into one trip. It's often faster to park once near the stores and walk from one to the next, but I know people who insist on driving their car from one end of the shopping center to the other end so that they don't have to walk its length. Use your bicycle more often: it saves lots of energy and it's better for your health. And why do you need to drive 50 miles to a restaurant when there are plenty of good ones much closer?<p>
<p style="font-size:110%">Americans use more energy per person than most other countries in the world. The average American uses more than four times as much energy as the average person elsewhere in the world. And it's not just because we're richer: we use twice as much as the average German or British citizen, and they're just as rich as we are. There are other countries that use more energy per capita than we do: oil-rich countries like Bahrain, Brunei, and Qatar, which have energy to burn (literally!); and perennially cold countries like Iceland and Canada, where people need lots of heat most of the year.<p>]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[<br/><a href="http://www.butchgraphics.com/3d/">thermostat image</a><br/>]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="Bicycling">
		<Text><![CDATA[<p style="font-size:110%">Bicycling is not only the most energy-efficience way to get around; it's also the fastest way for short trips or in cities. Very roughly speaking, a bicycle is faster than a car for distances of about three miles inside a city – but it depends a lot upon the city. Hilly cities or cities with enormous amounts of parking lean more in favor of cars; but flat or dense cities definitely give a big advantage to bicycles.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">In the typical American suburb, bicycles are faster than cars for trips of only a mile or so. But again, it depends a lot upon local conditions.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">The single most important local condition is the provision of bicycle lanes. These set aside safe space for bicyclists so that cars don't run them down. The bike lane shown in the photograph is just about the best possible: it's wide, it's one-way (to go in the opposite direction, you use the bike lane on the other side of the street); and it's protected from cars by a separate parking lane. Note also that the bike lane is not part of the sidewalk; bicyclists and pedestrians don't mix together. This bike lane is in Copenhaagen, Denmark, one of the most bicycle-friendly cities in the world. Note the traffic on the street: there are fewer cars than bicycles and pedestrians!</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">Another important factor is the provision of bike racks for bicycle parking. Some cities have plenty of bike racks; some have none. People can't use their bikes if they don't have bike racks near their destination.<p>
<p style="font-size:110%">American cities and towns tend to be more "bike tolerant" than "bike friendly". They usually have some bike lanes along important routes, but usually these consist of nothing more than a painted stripe along the shoulder – and motorists usually ignore the bike lane (and police seldom cite them for doing so). That's why riding a bike in America is four times more dangerous than in northern Europe. However, the city of Portland, Oregon, has implemented serious bike lanes and as a result enjoys a much lower accident rate for bicyclists than anywhere else in America.<p>
<p style="font-size:110%">An interesting twist is provided by a variety of "bike sharing" services that stock bike racks with lots of specially marked bikes. You can use any bike you find, unlocking it at one place, riding it to your destination, and locking it on a bike rack there. There are many variations on the scheme; in some places, the bikes are free to use because the city and its merchants want to reduce traffic congestion. In other places, you pay money to get a special card that unlocks the bike from the rack; in other places, you put deposit coins in the lock. In still more cases, you use your credit card, but the charge is trivial; the primary purpose of the credit card is to provide some protection against theft. Again, Europe leads the way in such schemes; there are only a few in America.<p>]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[<a href="http://www.streetsblog.org/wp-content/uploads/2006/10/IMG_0540_lane_inside_parkedcars.jpg">bike lane image</a><br/>]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="Big Cars">
		<Text><![CDATA[<p style="font-size:110%">The typical big American car gets less than 20 mpg, an engine with at least 300 horsepower, and has a top speed in excess of 100 mph. It can go from 0 to 60 mph in six seconds or less. Impressive, no? But think about it for a minute: when was the last time that you needed to go over 100 mph? When was the last time that you needed to accelerate from 0 to 60 mph in six seconds? Probably not recently. Probably never. So why would you want a car that does things that you don't need it to do? Would you buy a car with two spare tires? How about a car with a horn that plays Beethoven's Fifth Symphony? Maybe you'd be interested in a car with a steering wheel that dices onions in seconds (and, if you act now, they'll throw in some Ginsu knives)? Why should you pay for features that you'll never use?</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">Many American cars are too big, too fast, too powerful – and too wasteful. People in Europe get along perfectly well with cars having half the horsepower of American cars. In fact, people all over the world are quite happy in much smaller cars than we use.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">What's especially sad about this is that so many American families have two or even three cars. If you're going to have a lot of different cars, why not specialize: have a small car for commuting to work, and a big car for the whole family? Many families already do this, but there are still millions of families with multiple huge cars.<p>
<p style="font-size:110%">"But what about <a href="CarSafety">safety</a>?" you might ask. "Aren't big cars safer than small cars?" Not really: in most cases, the weight of the car is not as important as how it's driven.<p>
<p style="font-size:110%">There's plenty of room for Americans to cut down on the size of their cars without suffering any serious inconvenience.<p>]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[<a href="http://photocarsonline.com/images/20090513162525_2010-nissan-armada-suv-3.jpg">SUV image</a><br/>]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="Billion Gallons of Gasoline Equivalent">
		<Text><![CDATA[<p style="font-size:110%">Because energy is so important to our world, we have lots of different units of measurement. Most physicists use <i>Joules</i>, but some physicists use <i>electron volts</i>; dieticians use <i>calories</i>; air conditioners use <i>BTUs</i> (British Thermal Units); the oil industry uses <i>barrels</i>; electricity is measured in <i>KWh</i> (kilowatt-hours); at coal plants they use <i>tces</i> (ton of coal equivalent); nuclear bombs are measured in <i>tons of TNT</i> equivalent.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">Actually, the <b>real</b> reason there are so many ways to measure energy is to torture students. Did you know that there are 39.6832 million BTUs in 10 billion calories? Or that there are 0.0000002778 kilowatt hours in one Joule? There are, in fact 42 different conversion formulas for all these units of energy, so teachers love to make test questions like "How many gallons of gasoline (each containing 132 megaJoules) would it take to equal the destructive force of a 1 megaton hydrogen bomb, when one ton of TNT contains 4 billion Joules?" Test questions like these take lots of mental busywork but no real thinking. </p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">Obviously, I didn't want to use lots of different units of energy in this game; I had to pick one and use it for <b>all</b> forms of energy. I decided that the form of energy that most people have a feeling for is a gallon of gasoline. You really wouldn't <b>want</b> to get a feeling for one KWh of electricity, because the only way to do that is to get yourself electrocuted. For the same reason, you don't want to get a feeling for the energy content of a ton of TNT. And who wants to dig through a ton of coal? So a gallon of gasoline it is.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">Of course, you don't get gasoline coming out of the electricity socket, and you don't burn gasoline to heat your home. So we're really talking about the <i>energy equivalent</i> of a gallon of gasoline. For all you nerds reading this, here are the equivalents. One gallon of gasoline has the energy equivalet of 132 megaJoules, 132 thousand BTUs of heat, 37 KWh of electricity, or 31 million calories. Big deal.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">The amounts of energy humankind uses are so high that we end up talking about billions of gallons of gasoline, so the standard unit of energy in this game is a billion gallons of gasoline equivalent. That's as much as 30 kiloton bomb, or half of the amount of electricity generated by China's huge Three Gorges Dam in one year. It would take five supertankers to hold that much gasoline.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">Because "billion gallons of gasoline equivalent" is such a long, tiresome, tedious phrase to read, I'll just get snappy and call it a BgOge, which is pronounced "big oge", because it really is a lot of energy.</p>]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[<a href="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/7/75/Supertanker_AbQaiq.jpg">supertanker</a><br/>]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="Biomass">
		<Text><![CDATA[<p style="font-size:110%">This is new snazzy, high-tech term for "burning old dead stuff". We produce all sorts of stuff that we can't otherwise use. The most abundant source of biomass is the stuff left over from lumber production. When loggers cut down trees for lumber, there's a lot of wood that isn't used for lumber: all the branches (called <i>slash</i>), the bark, and various edges and loose ends of wood. This stuff goes into a huge Osterizer thing that chops it all up into chips; the chips can then be burned to make electricity. We can also burn some of the stuff that's left over from farming.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">Another way to use biomass is to chemically process it to make burnable methane gas; this works well with rice hulls (the stuff that's left over when we harvest rice) and corn stalks. </p>
		]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="Breeder Reactor">
		<Text><![CDATA[<p style="font-size:110%">99.3% of the uranium we dig out of the ground is useless as a source of nuclear energy; only 0.7% is usable. The difference is that uranium comes in three isotopes: U234, U235, and U238. Almost all of the uranium in the ground is U238; the rest is U235, with a tiny amount of U234. The U238 (the most abundant form) can't fuel a nuclear reactor, because it doesn't make the right kind of nuclear reactions. The U235 is the good stuff, so we have to separate the U235 from the U238. We do this with a special technology that's super-high-tech and super-secret, because you can make uranium for nuclear bombs with it – in fact, possession of that technology is the key to building nuclear bombs. You still need the technology to make fuel for nuclear reactors, but you don't have to concentrate the U235 as much. To make fuel for nuclear reactors, you need to concentrate the U235 from 0.7% to 3%, but to make bombs you need to concentrate it to 90%. This is all very expensive.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">Wouldn't it be nice if we could somehow use the U238 for fuel for our reactors? We have tons and tons of that stuff lying around left over after we separate out the U235. It turns out, there's a way to utilize U238. If you hit it with lots of neutrons, it will convert into plutonium 239, which can be used for fuel in nuclear reactors. The problem is, you need gazillions of neutrons to convert U238 into Pu239. Where you gonna get gazillions of neutrons?</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">Answer: on the sides of a nuclear reactor! You see, nuclear reactors rely on a nuclear reaction in which one U235 nucleus splits into pieces, releasing gobs of energy and three extra neutrons. We need just one of those neutrons to hit another U235 nucleus to keep the chain reaction going; that leaves two extra neutrons, which fly out of the reactor and get lost. That's what gives us the our source of neutrons. We just pack lots of U238 around the sides of the reactor, and some of those extra neutrons will hit U238 nuclei and convert them into Pu239 nuclei.<p>
<p style="font-size:110%">Here's the really wild thing about this design: it will generate more usable fuel than it burns. In other words, we can set up a breeder reactor with a load of fuel, and it will generate enough fuel to keep itself going forever – with plenty of extra fuel to use in other reactors! It's like a car that manufactures its own gasoline as it runs!<p>
<p style="font-size:110%">This is not magic; we're not getting something for nothing. Here's an analogy: suppose that it's a rainy night and you're trying to get a campfire going. You've got plenty of wet wood, but it won't burn. But you do have just enough dry wood to get the campfire burning well. So you pile up wet wood around the fire, and the heat of the fire dries out the wet wood as it burns. If you set it up properly, you can dry out wood faster than you burn it, manufacturing extra dry wood for later.<p>
<p style="font-size:110%">If you know anything about technology, you should always ask, "What's the catch?" There are <b>two</b> nasty catches with breeder reactors. The first catch is that you're making plutonium, which is just about the nastiest stuff in the world. It's extremely dangerous; just a tiny mote of plutonium inside your lung will cause lung cancer. Worse, it's perfect stuff for making bombs, because it's easy to concentrate and purify – you don't need all that high-tech top-secret, expensive technology to get bomb material. You just do some chemistry to it and voila! – lots of stuff for making nuclear bombs.<p>
<p style="font-size:110%">"Big deal", you say, "we don't need any more nuclear bombs, we've got too many already." That's true – but we're not the ones to worry about. What if, say, some nasty country that hates us gets its hands on a breeder reactor? It will start generating lots of plutonium and making bombs.<p>
<p style="font-size:110%"> There are already too many countries with nuclear bombs – we don't want any more. So about forty years ago we set up something called the Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty – the NPT. It's a simple deal: any country that signs the treaty promises never to make bombs; in return, we promise that we will let them have any and all peaceful nuclear technology that we are using. Almost all the countries in the world have signed the NPT. That's good, right?<p>
<p style="font-size:110%">But suppose that we start using breeder reactors commercially. That means that breeder reactors are peaceful nuclear technology, which means that any country that signed the NPT can demand that we sell them the breeder reactor technology so that they can have breeder reactors. Once they have working breeder reactors, it's all too easy for them to extract the plutonium and start making bombs on the sly – and there's not much we can do to prevent them from doing that. In other words, breeder reactors plus NPT equals proliferation! How's that for a catch?<p>
<p style="font-size:110%">But that's only the first catch. The second catch involves safety. Generation II reactors – the kind that we use right now – are really quite safe; even if you hit them with a record-setting earthquake and a monster tsunami, they do a pretty good job of protecting the public from danger. Breeder reactors aren't quite as safe. In the first place, they can't use water as a coolant; they have to use things like molten lead or molten sodium to cool the reactor. Liquid sodium burns if exposed to the air. It's one thing to have radioactive water leaking out from a nuclear power plant; if instead it's liquid sodium leaking and burning, that makes matters more complicated. We don't have much experience with these exotic cooling systems, so it's difficult to be certain that they'll be safe.<p>
<p style="font-size:110%">There's another concern. It is theoretically impossible for a Generation II nuclear power plant to explode like a nuclear bomb. That's not the case with breeder reactors. Under some conditions, it's theoretically possible for a breeder reactor to suffer a nuclear explosion. You can be certain that the designers of these reactors have come up with all sorts of clever schemes to make certain that this could never actually happen, but again, we don't have a lot of operating experience with breeder reactors, so we can't be sure.<p>]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="Carbon Capture Technology">
		<Text><![CDATA[<p style="font-size:110%">Here's a bright idea: instead of sending the combustion gases from a coal power plant into a smokestack and then into the atmosphere, why not pump them deep into the ground where they can't do any harm? This idea is called "carbon capture and storage". We start with the "flue gases" – the stuff that would normally go up the smokestack and out into the atmosphere. Instead, we pipe those flue gases to a huge cooling chamber where we cool them down and then send them down a big pipe to a location where they are pumped under high pressure deep into the ground. We have to carefully select the place where we bury the flue gases, because we don't want them to leak out. Fortunately, there's a good use we can put these flue gases to. If we pump them into the ground near a big oilfield, they'll help push the oil into our oil wells where we can get it. While the basic technology for carbon sequestration has been around for a while, it is still expensive. Moreover, it takes a lot of energy to do all this cooling and pumping: between 25% and 40% of a coal plant's output. Thus, carbon sequestration technology decreases the amount of energy we can get from coal. There are currently four large carbon sequestration facilities in the world, which together sequestrate about 4.5 million tons of CO2 every year.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">If you want to sound like you know what you're talking about, call it <i>carbon capture and sequestration</i>. If you want to sound like an expert, call it <i>CC&S<i.]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carbon_capture">Wikipedia</a><br/><a href="http://www.fossil.energy.gov/programs/sequestration/index.html">What the Department of Energy is doing</a><br/><a href="http://www.scientificamerican.com/report.cfm?id=carbon-capture-storage-ccs">Scientific American website on carbon capture</a><br/><a href="http://www.ccsassociation.org/faqs/ccs-general/">An industry association for carbon capture</a>]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="Carbon Cycle">
		<Text><![CDATA[<p style="font-size:110%">There are lots of things that emit carbon dioxide into the air. Many of the chemical reactions going inside your body consume oxygen and release carbon dioxide. When you inhale, oxygen from the atmosphere enters your lungs and mixes into your blood cells, which carry it to every cell in your body. Meanwhile, all the carbon dioxide produced by those cells mixes into your blood, which carries it to the lungs. There it moves into the air that you exhale. So you inhale oxygen and exhale carbon dioxide. The same thing goes for every animal and insect on this planet.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">If the world had only animals, we'd use up all the oxygen. But plants do the reverse: they take carbon dioxide out of the air and break it up to get the carbon they need. The oxygen that's left over just gets dumped into the air.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">Some of the carbon that the plants use gets eaten by animals; some gets buried in the soil; some gets eaten by bacteria when the plants rot. Most of the carbon that's eaten eventually gets back into the atmosphere when the animals or bacteria release carbon dioxide. If that plant material gets buried under sediments and ends up deep underground, most of it eventually forms oil, coal, or natural gas.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">The ocean also participates in the carbon cycle. It absorbs some of the carbon dioxide to make carbonic acid; this causes ocean acidification.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">Thus we have a huge process called the <i>carbon cycle</i>. Carbon goes round and round, from atmosphere to plant to animal and back to the atmosphere. This cycle was in a nice stable equilibrium until we humans came along and started burning stuff, putting a lot more carbon dioxide into the atmosphere. The total amount we put in is small potatoes compared to the size of the overall cycle. But it was in balance before we came along, and by butting in, we altered the balance. Beforehand, about 200 gigatons of carbon dioxide flowed into the atmosphere and back out every year, for a net change of zero. We added about 6 measly gigatons – but it was all going in, with none coming out. So every year, 206 gigatons flowed into the atmosphere, and only 200 gigatons came out. Do this long enough, and pretty soon you get a whole lotta gigatons in the atmosphere.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">Some climate change deniers ("pants on fire!") like to say that the amount we put into the air is just too tiny to make a difference. Suppose that I were to hack into the bank account of one of these deniers and put in a little virus that stole just one cent of every dollar that he deposited into his account. That's only one-hundredth as much as he's adding to his account. But he's also taking money out of his account, and the overall account was in balance – until I hacked it. Now I'm steadily draining it away, and eventually he'll go broke. A small, steady change to a system that was in equilibrium will eventually alter it big-time. That's what we humans are doing to the atmosphere.</p>]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[<a href="http://climatechange.procon.org/files/1-climate-change-images/carbon-dioxide-is-released-and-absorbed-in-the-global-carbon-cycle-picture.jpg">diagram</a><br/>]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="Chernobyl">
		<Text><![CDATA[<p style="font-size:110%">The accident at Chernobyl in 1986 was far and away the most serious accident at any nuclear power plant. The magnitude of the disaster can be grasped by a few numbers. The first is the number of deaths attributable to the accident. There is considerable controversy regarding this number; estimates range from a low of 4,000 to a high of over a million. My own study of the accident leads me to conclude that the most likely value is about 10,000 deaths. The second number is the total economic cost of the accident, which is more reliably estimated at something over $200 billion. The third number is the amount of land still uninhabitable 25 years after the accident: 6,000 square miles. Initially about 120,000 people lived in this zone; now only a few stubborn squatters remain. About the only upside is that wildlife, unhindered by human interference, has grown enormously in the area.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">The accident was caused by a combination of poor design and truly idiotic behavior on the part of the operators. Ironically, the accident was triggered by an incompetently performed safety experiment. The experiment had been designed and developed over the course of several years, and had already been performed, unsuccessfully, a number of times.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">The fundamental cause of the accident was a failure to abort the experiment after the conditions deviated from the planned experimental parameters. Instead, the fools running the experiment thought that they could improvise. You don't improvise with a 4,000 MW nuclear reactor.<p>
<p style="font-size:110%">The catalog of mistakes they made would make Homer Simpson blush with embarrassment. Their basic failure was not realizing that nuclear reactors can't be switched on and off like light bulbs. They must be brought up to full power in a smooth linear process; even more important, the process of shutting a reactor down must be done cleanly. Instead, these morons kept jiggling the control rods up and down, trying to get the exact power level they needed for the experiment. It's as if the pilot of an airplane coming in for a landing kept jerking the nose of the plane up and down trying to stay on the prescribed flight path instead of just coming in smoothly. And guess what? When you jerk a reactor around, it doesn't behave the way you expect it to.<p>
<p style="font-size:110%">To make a long story short, the reactor blew up. There were several explosions. One was a steam explosion and the other was probably a small nuclear explosion. When it blew up, highly radioactive chunks of the reactor shot up into the air and crashed to earth all around the plant. Then the graphite moderator caught fire and burned furiously, sending up intensely radioactive smoke that spread all over Europe.<p>
<p style="font-size:110%">Much of the blame, though, goes to two crucial flaws in the design of the plant. In the first place, it was a graphite reactor. These are powerful and physically efficient reactors, but they are intrinsically unsafe, because extremely hot graphite burns like a demon when exposed to oxygen. The plant operators were sure that there was no way that oxygen could get to the graphite – until the explosion. Once the graphite caught fire, there was nothing that could be done to stop it. No western nation has ever permitted the construction of a large graphite reactor because they are intrinsically unsafe. The only graphite reactors built in the West have been small research reactors.<p>
<p style="font-size:110%">The second crucial flaw was the absence of a containment structure. All Western reactors are built with huge containment structures – concrete shells ten feet thick with enormous amounts of huge steel rebar inside. The Soviets thought they didn't need no stinkin' safety features like containment structures. So when the reactor at Chernobyl exploded, there was nothing to stop all that radioactivity from going right out the roof and into the atmosphere.<p>
<p style="font-size:110%">The lousy safety standards of the Soviet nuclear industry were well known in the west. When somebody first told me of the Chernobyl accident, my reaction was, "Well, it finally happened." I wasn't the least bit surprised.<p>
<p style="font-size:110%"><p>]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[<a href="http://www.funniez.net/images/stories/chernobyl/chernobyl-033.jpg">Chernobyl photo</a><br/>]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="Chris Crawford">
		<Text><![CDATA[<p style="font-size:110%">Chris Crawford (that's me in the photo) designed, programmed, and wrote this program. I am solely responsible for its content, so if you think I screwed up, I'm the one to blame. If you think I did a great job, I'm the one to thank.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">I used to be a big-shot game designer back in the ancient days when we programmed with stone tools. I gave all that up to work on interactive storytelling, which didn't work out. So I wrote this program to earn a little money so that I can get back to working on interactive storytelling.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">So please don't pirate this program. It's cheap, it's good, and it deserves to be paid for. Besides, look at those puppy eyes – how could you deny me?]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="Clean Coal">
		<Text><![CDATA[<p style="font-size:110%">Let's face it: coal is the filthiest, most environmentally destructive source of energy on the planet (except for burning tires). People have been working on ways to clean up coal burning for decades now, and some of the technologies are already in use, while others are still years away.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%"><b>Electrostatic precipitators</b> are one of the oldest cleanup technologies. Do you recall how little bits of paper and fuzz will be attracted to a static-y wool sweater when you first put it on? Static electricity attracts tiny things, and the tinier they are, the better it attracts them. So they set up a bunch of metal plates and charge them up to a few thousand volts and run the smoke from the burning coal through them. The tiny smoke particles stick to the plates, so the smoke coming out has fewer particles. These devices typically catch more than 99% of the particulates. Remeber, though, that we burn so much that we still get a lot particulates going out the smokestacks: coal plants all over the world release about 10 million tons of particulates each year.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%"><b>Scrubbers:</b> This technology sprays a mixture of water and limestone through the outgoing smoke to chemically capture some of the worst pollutants. The good news is that these things are pretty good: the best of them capture most of the sulfur dioxide. The bad news is that the chemical reaction that absorbs the sulfur dioxide also releases even <b>more</b> carbon dioxide into the atmosphere. Oops!</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%"><b>Coal gasification:</b> The idea here is to refrain from burning the coal in the first place. Instead, we pulverize it and spray high-temperature steam over it. This triggers a chemical reaction that produces a gas containing carbon monoxide and hydrogen, and black icky sludge. The carbon monoxide is poisonous but it burns along with the hydrogen, releasing only carbon dioxide and water. How's that for clean? Of course, there is the little matter of the billions of tons of black icky sludge that we still have to get rid of, but at least it's all on one place, so we can dispose of it properly. </p>]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[<a href="http://www.yildiz.edu.tr/~erturk/course_notes/air_pol_control/air5.pdf">super-technical article on electrostatic precipitators</a>]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="Coal Liquifaction">
		<Text><![CDATA[<p style="font-size:110%">During World War II, the Germans could never get enough gasoline. Most of what they had came from Romania, and when the Red Army captured that area in 1944, the Germans no longer had a source of gasoline. However, their tanks and planes didn't come grinding to a halt; they had figured out a way to make gasoline from coal, which they had plenty of. This process was not cheap, but it worked and was able to keep the German armies in operation for another year.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">Since then, there have been many attempts to improve on the process of converting coal into gasoline. In the first place, we have so much coal that, if we could convert it into gasoline, we wouldn't have to worry about gasoline supplies for a long, long time. In the second place, converting filthy coal into cleaner gasoline should permit us to trap all the nasty pollutants at the factory, making it easier to keep them out of the environment.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">There is one thing about coal liquifaction that has always mystified me: why isn't it called "coal liquification"?</p>]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Coal_liquefaction">Wikipedia on coal liquifaction</a><br>
		<a href="http://thefraserdomain.typepad.com/energy/2005/07/about_coal_liqu.html">a good blog post about coal liquifaction</a><br/>
		<a href="http://www.worldcoal.org/coal/uses-of-coal/coal-to-liquids/">The coal industry's view</a><br/>
		<a href="http://www.bloomberg.com/apps/news?pid=newsarchive&sid=a3SIXbVZ8JiE">Chinese plans for coal liquifaction</a><br><br><br><br><br><br><br><br><br><br><a href="http://wattsupwiththat.files.wordpress.com/2008/04/lump_of_coal.jpg>lump of coal</a><br>
		<a href="http://www.clker.com/cliparts/o/d/E/b/0/o/gasoline-pump-nozzle-hi.png">gasoline spigot</a>]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="Climate Change">
		<Text><![CDATA[<p style="font-size:110%">Although "Global Warming" is the term you hear most of the time, it's not the best term, because it's misleading. Scientists prefer the term "Climate Change". Sometimes you'll read about "Anthropogenic Climate Change" – that means "climate change caused by people". "Anthropogenic" is just hoity-toity for "caused by people". If you sneeze and get snot all over the place, call it "Sneezogenic Snot" and perhaps people will be so impressed that they won't mind.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">What's wrong with the term "Global Warming"? Well, in the first place, the warming won't show up everywhere. It'll be really strong in the polar regions (it is already wreaking havoc around the Arctic), but around the equator, people won't notice much increase in temperature at all. However, they will notice other effects, such as changes in when and how much rain they get. Some areas of the planet will end up drier, while other areas will end up wetter. Some areas will experience more storms and flooding, while other areas may end up with fewer storms and flooding. The sea level will rise, and that will affect everybody.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">Although the average temperature for the earth as a whole will rise, there are so many other effects, and they're spread so widely, that it's better to call it "climate change".<p>
<p style="font-size:110%">Anthropogenic climate change really is easy to understand with just a little science background, so if you want to learn how it works, <a href="Light">start here</a>. </p>
<p style="font-size:110%">You may have heard some people claim that climate change is all a big hoax, that it's not real. There's no nice way to say this: <a href="Deniers">those people are liars</a>. They deny climate change for political reasons, not scientific ones.</p>]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[<a href="http://soundwaves.usgs.gov/2009/05/polar-bears-3-largeLG.jpg">polar bear photo</a><br/>]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="Concentrated Solar Thermal Energy">
		<Text><![CDATA[<p style="font-size:110%">A <a href="Thermal%20Power%20Plant">thermal power plant</a> uses a source of heat to make electricity. There are plenty of ways to make heat: burning coal, oil, or natural gas, or by nuclear reactions, or by tapping the geothermal heat of the earth. We can also use sunlight as a source of heat for a thermal power plant; there are several ways to to do this.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">The most commonly used technology uses a <i>parabolic trough</i>. To visualize this system, start by thinking of a big pipe maybe ten feet in diameter. Cut it in half lengthwise so that you get a long trough that has a cross-section that's a half-circle. Next, imagine changing the shape so that the cross-section is a parabola instead of a half-circle. Make the inner surface of the parabola shiny like a mirror. Lastly, mount a small pipe in the place that was once the center of the big pipe.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">Now put this contraption outside in the sun, running from east to west. The sunlight will be focused by the mirror onto the little pipe, which will get really hot. Pump water through that little pipe and the water will get really hot, so hot that it will boil into steam. Let the steam go through a turbine connected to a generator, and voila! Electricity!</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">But there's another way to make electricity from sunlight: build a tall tower with a big black water container at the top. Then set up acres of mirrors around it, each one at a different angle to reflect sunlight directly onto the water tank at the top of the tower. All that sunlight focused on the water tank gets the water so hot that it boils into steam. Send the steam to a turbine, yada, yada, yada, and you've got electricity!</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">But wait! There's more! Ginzu knife solar generators! No, I'm kidding... but there <b>is</b> another way to make solar electricity. It uses parabolic mirror dishes (like big radar dishes) that focus sunlight onto a small <a href="Stirling%20Engine">Stirling engine</a>, which makes electricity.</p>]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[<a href="http://www.archimedesolarenergy.it/images/parabolic_trough2.jpg">parabolic trough</a><br/><a href="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/6/64/Dish_Stirling_Systems_of_SBP_in_Spain.JPG">Stirling dish</a><br/><a href="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/e/eb/PS10_solar_power_tower.jpg">solar power tower</a><br/>]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="Condenser">
		<Text><![CDATA[<p style="font-size:110%">Water from warm air naturally condenses on the surface of any cold object. This happens whenever the object is colder than the air. So imagine what happens when you take something reasonably cool, like a pipe filled with cool water, and blow superheated steam over it. The steam will condense into water. If you keep pumping more cool water into the pipe, so that it stays cool, and more steam against it, then you'll get lots of water condensing.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">This is how a condenser in a power plant works, but it's done on a humongous scale. We pump hundreds of gallons of cool water into it, and pipe enormous amounts of steam into it, the steam condenses into water, and we get lots of water coming out the bottom. Think about it: this is exactly the opposite of what the heat source in a power plant does. The heat source boils water into steam, and the condenser condenses steam back into water.<p>
<p style="font-size:110%"> Now, when water boils into steam, it expands to 1700 times its regular volume; when steam condenses into water, it contracts to just 1/1700th of its volume. So the steam going into the turbine is at very high pressure, while the steam coming out of the turbine is at much lower pressure because the condenser is shrinking all that steam back into water. That huge difference in pressure is what makes the turbine turn so fast. The high-pressure steam is pushing <b>really</b> hard to get to the low-pressure steam area.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">"Hold it right there!" I hear you say. "Where do you get all the cool water that goes into the condenser?" That requires a <a href="Hyperbolic%20Cooling%20Tower">hyperbolic cooling tower</a><p>]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[<br/>]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="Controlling Reactions">
		<Text><![CDATA[<p style="font-size:110%">A nuclear power plant uses nuclear reactions to generate heat, but the uranium in a nuclear power plant is not squeezed together tightly enough to detonate like a nuclear bomb. Instead, the uranium fuel is made of little pellets that are stacked into fuel rods; bunches of fuel rods grouped together (with space between them) make up the core of the reactor. We can control the speed of the reactions by shoving special control rods in between the fuel rods. The control rods are made of elements that love to gobble up neutrons. So when we put the control rods down into the reactor, between the fuel rods, they block neutrons from moving from one fuel rod to the next, which cuts down on the number of nuclear reactions taking place. By moving different control rods up or down, we can precisely control how much heat the reactor produces.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">But there's always a catch, and with nuclear reactors, the catch is that the uranium atoms aren't the only things inside the reactor that are making energy. You see, when a uranium nucleus fissions, it breaks into smaller nuclei. Now, if you carry out a scientific experiment by lining up a bunch of glasses and hitting each one with a hammer, you will observe (if you haven't lost an eye to flying shards of glass) that the glasses don't break up the same way each time. They break up into different shaped pieces of glass. Uranium atoms are the same way: they break up into different smaller nuclei.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">Sometimes we get lucky and those smaller nuclei are normal, everyday nuclei. But many times the smaller nuclei are not normal; they're like mutants. They're radioactive, which means that they're just not put together right. They'll sit there for a few microseconds, or a few minutes, or a few decades, and then, for no reason at all, they'll fission, just like the uranium nucleus did. When they fission, they release lots of energy and – surprise, surprise – <b>more neutrons</b>! Those neutrons then fly off to break up more uranium nuclei, so the reactor continues to generate heat even <b>after</b> you've turned it off!<p>]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="Costs of Nuclear Power">
		<Text><![CDATA[<p style="font-size:110%">The worst problem with nuclear power plants is that they're hideously expensive. There was a time when it seemed that they would produce oodles of power cheaply, but as the years rolled by and safety problems arose, people had to put more and more safety equipment on, raising the price. Worse, the plants had be built slowly and carefully, with careful inspections at each stage of construction. If it wasn't perfect, they'd have to tear out the defective sections and do them all over again. This slowed things down even more. Nowadays it can take ten years to build a nuclear power plant.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">The base price of a nuclear power plant is a few billion dollars. However, all that money has be spent building the plant, before it starts earning any money. So the people building the plant have to borrow, say, $2 billion to get started. Can you imagine the interest costs on $2 billion? They run about $100 million per year. So if it takes 10 years to build the plant, you end up paying a billion dollar just for interest costs, raising the cost from $2 billion to $3 billion.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">It gets worse. Every time there's a problem anywhere, it delays construction. When you're paying interest of about $30,000 every single day, delays of a week here and a week there start adding a lot of interest costs.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">Then there's the uncertainty factor. Banks like safe investments. If they think that something might go wrong with the project, and they might not get their money back, they raise the interest rate. If the banks decide to charge you 6% interest instead of 5% interest, that addition 1% will add an extra $100 million to your costs.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">The banks have good reason to worry: they may trust you, but how do they know that the government won't kill your project? The accident at Fukushima caused Germany to decide not to build any more nuclear power plants. Anybody who had spent money developing a new nuclear power plant lost all their money. Is politics predictable? Are you willing to bet $2 billion on the predictability of politics?]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="Deniers">
		<Text><![CDATA[<p style="font-size:110%">Fifty years ago evidence began to emerge showing that smoking is harmful to your health. The tobacco industry denied this strenuously and insisted that there was no scientific proof that smoking is bad for your health. For years they paid some scientists to deny the truth and publish scientific papers questioning the research that showed how harmful smoking can be. It took decades, but science eventually overcame the lies, and nowadays only cranks say that smoking isn't harmful to your health</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">But now we have the same thing all over again, only this time it's with climate change. Once again there are big companies (oil companies instead of tobacco companies) that are spending lots of money trying to confuse people about the truth. Once again there are people who put politics ahead of science and deny climate change. Once again the media are full of contradictory claims about a scientific subject. Once again the public doesn't know what to think.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">The best way for you to figure all this out for yourself is to study the science for yourself. To understand it properly, you'd probably need to study it in college for at least four years, and even then you'd just know the basics. To really understand it well, you'd have to devote at least ten years of your life to studying all the science. Whos' got time for that?</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">There are four steps you can take to make your own informed decision. The first step is to read through the very brief materials here in this game.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">The second step is to read the best brochure I've ever found on climate change. It's from the National Academy of Sciences and is free to download <a href="http://dels.nas.edu/resources/static-assets/materials-based-on-reports/reports-in-brief/Science-Report-Brief-final.pdf">right here</a>.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">The third step is to read some of the better blogs. The blog I recommend for beginners is <a href="http://climatecrocks.com/">Climate Denial Crock of the Week</a>. You can find a good debunking of the lies coming from the deniers at <a href="http://www.skepticalscience.com">Skeptical Science</a>. If you want to get really down and dirty, you can read what real scientists are talking about at <a href="http://www.realclimate.org/">Real Climate<a/>.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">The fourth thing you can do is trust the best scientists in America. Denialists like to say that there's disagreement among scientists about climate change, but that's a lie. The <b>National Academy of Sciences</b> was set up nearly 150 years ago to provide Congress with reliable advice on scientific matters that might affect public policy. In 150 years, the National Academy of Sciences has issued hundreds of reports to Congress, and in all that time, there has never been a single statement in any report to Congress that was later found to be untrue. These folks have a perfect track record! And if you want to know what they have to say about climate change, just read the brochure I described in Step 2.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">But maybe you don't want to trust the American National Academy of Sciences. OK, that's fine. Pick a country, any country; if it has a national academy of science of its own, then it has endorsed the idea of anthropogenic climate change. Here are the countries with national academy of sciences that have done exactly that: Australia, Belgium, Brazil, Cameroon, Canada, China, France, Ghana, Germany, Indonesia, Ireland, Italy, India, Japan, Kenya, Madagascar, Malaysia, Mexico, Nigeria, New Zealand, Poland, Russia, Senegal, South Africa, Sudan, Sweden, Tanzania, Turkey, Uganda, United Kingdom Zambia, and Zimbabwe. The climate change deniers will jump on the fact that this list leaves out such countries as Andorra, Liechtenstein, The Gambia, and Afghanistan...</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">Still not convinced? How about this list of scientific and professional organizations that have published resolutions in support of the theory of anthropogenic climate change: American Association for the Advancement of Science, American Chemical Society, American Insitute of Physics, American Physical Society, Australian Institute of Physics, European Physical Society, European Science Foundation, Federation of Australian Scientific and Technological Societies, American Geophysical Union, European Federation of Geologists, European Geosciences Union, Geological Society of America, Geological Society of London, International Union of Geodesy and Geophysics, National Association of Geoscience Teachers, American Meteorological Society, Australian Meteorological and Oceanographic Society, American Association of People Who Go Crazy Reading Long Lists, Canadian Foundation for Climate and Atmospheric Sciences, Canadian Meteorological and Oceanographic Society, Royal Meteorological Society, World Meteorological Organization, American Quaternary Association, and the International Union for Quaternary Research.</p>
		]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[<br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/>Images:<br/><a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_Pg5B42oQLmM/TK935C_BPWI/AAAAAAAAPoQ/ecmINkqS0M0/s1600/smoking_doctor.jpg">cigarette ad image</a><br/><a href="http://climateconference.heartland.org/wp-content/uploads/2011/05/no-climate-change-nyc-020b-med.jpg">global warming ad image</a>]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="Different Volts for Different Folks">
		<Text><![CDATA[<p style="font-size:110%">One of the benefits of the grid is that it allows us to move electricity from places that have extra to places that don't have enough. This is valuable because it allows us to average out all the little bobbles and variations in the supply of and demand for electricity.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">It's sort of like a potluck dinner: everybody brings something different to the meal and eats something different. If there are enough people participating, then it all pretty much averages out. There'll probably be plenty of food to meet the different tastes of different people.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">This is really valuable when we start bringing in intermittent sources of electricity like solar and wind. These sources don't always provide the right amount of electricity at the right time, but if we hook them into a big enough grid, there'll probably be enough electricity from them and other sources to average out nicely.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">But there is a limitation on the usefulness of the grid: <a href="Transmission%20Losses">transmission losses</a>. The longer the transmission line, the higher the loss of electricity. So it really wouldn't be practical to ship solar electricity from Arizona to New York: we'd lose too much of the electricity moving it that far. Roughly speaking, the typical transmission line is good for moving power only about 500 miles. Any further than that and you start losing too much electricity.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">Let's get back to the example of the pot luck dinner. Suppose that there were no cars. People couldn't travel very far, so the only people coming to the pot luck would be your closest neighbors. With that small a group, the pot luck might not work out well. Mrs. Jones and Mrs. Pederson would both bring their potato salad, and there'd be nothing good to eat. But with cars, more people would come, bringing a larger variety of dishes. Suppose that we had transporters that allowed people from all over the planet to come instantly. Then we'd get a huge pot luck with all kinds of different dishes from different countries. Wouldn't that be a great pot luck? The lesson is that the greater the distance you can reach, the better things work out. And it's the same way with electricity: the further we can economically transmit electricity, the more efficiently the whole grid works.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">But it all depends on how high the voltage is. Higher voltages can travel further. Which brings us to a new technology that could be more important to solar and wind than anything else: <a href="High%20Voltage%20Direct%20Current">HVDC (High Voltage Direct Current)</a>.</p>]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="Diminishing Returns">
		<Text><![CDATA[<p style="font-size:110%">Suppose there's a cute {boy|girl} that you'd like to impress. So you buy {him|her} a {videogame|book} as a present. {He|she} is pleased with the present. So you decide to buy {him|her} another present, then another, and another, and another. By the fifth present, {he|she} isn't so impressed, and by the tenth present, {he|she} isn't the slightest bit pleased. This is called <i>diminishing returns</i>: the more money you put into something, the less the effect. Most of the things we spend money on suffer from the effect of diminishing returns. There are only so many computers, shoes, hamburgers, cars, cameras, cellphones, cough drops, and {boy|girl}friends you can enjoy.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">It also applies at the big scale. For example, subways are a really efficient way to move people around in big cities, and it's good to extend the subways further out into the suburbs.  We could extend subways all the way to Podunktown, Nebraska, or Armpitville, Nevada, but not many people would use those subways, so we wouldn't get much value out of them. Spending enormous amounts of money on subways yields diminishing returns.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">Here's another example: we can build scrubbers for coal-burning power plants that remove 99% of the sulfur dioxide and nitrous oxides. If we wanted to, we could build even better scrubbers that remove 99.5% of the pollutants – but those more powerful scrubbers would cost us a lot more money to get that extra 0.5%. And if we wanted to get 99.9% of the pollutants, the scrubbers to do that would cost a humongous amount of money. That's diminishing returns for ya.</p>]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Diminishing_returns">Wikipedia weighs in on diminishing returns</a><br/><a href="http://www.wowwiki.com/Diminishing_returns">diminishing returns in World of Warcraft</a>]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="Drought">
		<Text><![CDATA[<p style="font-size:110%">Droughts are lengthy periods during which an insufficient amount of rain falls in a region. Droughts are exacerbated by high temperatures, because plants need more water when it's hotter. Droughts have plagued humanity for all of history, but the last ten years have seen larger, longer, and more serious droughts than any previous time. In South America, the Amazon basin has suffered from several droughts that contributed to huge forest fires. Australia has long had droughts but over the last ten years, it has experienced the most severe long-term drought in its history. The Sahel region along the southern edge of the Sahara desert in Africa has been experiencing a long-term drought for years now, and the Sahara desert is expanding southward. The drought in Texas in 2011 set records and has caused economic losses of at least $5 billion – and it's not over yet. Drought in Kenya and Somalia has triggered a famine that has killed over 100,000 people. All over the globe, droughts are hotter, drier, and more frequent.</p>]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[dry lake: USDA<br/>]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="Economies of Scale">
		<Text><![CDATA[<p style="font-size:110%">Suppose that you need to dig a small hole, and you know that it's the only hole you'll need to dig in your whole life. The most economical strategy would be to dig it with your bare hands, or maybe use a nearby stick or rock to dig it.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">Now suppose that you are planting a small garden. You know that you'll have to dig a number of holes, so you decide to purchase a shovel. It's a small investment, but it will greatly increase the efficiency of your hole-digging.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">Now suppose that you need to dig a lot of big, deep holes, say for construction. A shovel just won't do for this; you need an excavator like the one in the picture.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">There's a pattern here: the bigger the job, the bigger – and more expensive – the tool you need to do the job. And the cost per pound of dug dirt falls dramatically. An excavator will cost you $100,000, while a shovel might cost you only $10. The excavator costs 10,000 times as much as the shovel. But it will dig up a lot more than 10,000 times as much dirt, so in terms of dollars per pound of dirt, the excavator is cheaper than the shovel.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">This basic principle is called <i>economies of scale</i>: the bigger you get, the more efficient you are, and the lower the cost to get the same result.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">Economies of scale are the exact opposite of <a href="Diminishing Returns">diminishing returns</a>. With economies of scale, the bigger your effort, the <u>more</u> efficient it is. But with diminishing returns, the bigger your purchase, the <u>less</u> you get for it. The difference comes in the use. When you're making things (manufacturing), you get economies of scale. When you're buying things, you get diminishing returns. An excavator is a lot more efficient than a shovel, but having a thousand shirts isn't ten times better than having a hundred shirts.</p>]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="Electric Cars">
		<Text><![CDATA[<p style="font-size:110%">The basic design of an electric car is very simple. Instead of a gas tank, there's a battery. Instead of a gasoline engine, there's an electric motor. A gasoline engine uses hundreds of parts; an electric motor has a few dozen.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">Electric motors have a huge advantage over gasoline engines: they have their highest <i>torque</i> at low speeds, while gasoline engines have their lowest torque at low speeds. Torque is "twisting power": the power to make the wheels turn even when there's a big load. Horsepower measures how much power an engine can deliver at its best speed; torque measures how much power it can deliver when starting to move.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">This is important because the first job of any car engine is to get the car moving from a stop. An electric motor can do that directly, but gasoline engines have to be spinning pretty fast to have enough power to get the car moving. That creates a problem: if the wheels aren't turning at all and the engine is turning fast, how do you connect the engine to the wheels without a clash? We solve this problem with a <i>clutch</i>, a pair of disks that rub against each other. One disk connects to the engine, the other to the wheels. When you press down on the clutch pedal, you separate the two disks. As you slowly release the clutch pedal, the two disks start rubbing together lightly, and some of the fast spinning of the engine-disk starts the wheel-disk spinning slowly. As you release the clutch pedal, the two disks rub together more tightly and more of the engine's spinning is transmitted to the wheels. If you release the clutch pedal too fast, then the engine won't have enough torque to make the wheels spin, and the car lurches to a halt. The ideal technique is particuarly difficult for student drivers to learn.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">Most of the power of an engine is used to get the car moving. Electric motors do this easily, but gasoline engines don't, so you need a lot of extra power from the gasoline engine to accomplish what a smaller electric motor can do. That's why electric cars don't need as much power as gasoline cars: they're more efficient at starting the car.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">The greatest weakness of electric cars is their batteries. A pound of gasoline stores a lot more energy than a pound of battery; to carry enough energy to equal a tank of gasoline, you'd need more than a ton of batteries. Your electric car would be so heavy that it wouldn't go very fast.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">But researchers have been developing ever more powerful batteries that can store more energy, making electric cars better. The other big advance is in materials science: researchers are coming up with lighter, stronger materials to build a car with. A lighter car doesn't need as much energy to go fast, so that makes electric cars even more practical.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">Despite these advances, it is unlikely that electric cars will ever completely replace gasoline engines. Most likely, we'll see electric cars used for commuting and big diesel engines used for long-haul trucking. Between these two extremes, there will be some mixing of the two types.</p>
		]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[
		<a href="http://www.howstuffworks.com/electric-car.htm">a detailed explanation of electric cars</a><br>
		<a href="http://www.nissanusa.com/electric-cars/leaf/">The Nissan Leaf</a><br>
		<a href="http://www.ford.com/cars/focus/trim/electric/">The Ford Focus</a><br>
		<a href="http://www.teslamotors.com">Tesla super-snazzy electric cars</a><br>
		]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="Energy and Transportation">
		<Text><![CDATA[<p style="font-size:110%">The biggest savings are to be found in transportation. <a href="Walking">Walking</a> gets the equivalent of about 300 mpg (miles per gallon of gasoline); <a href="Bicycling">bicycling</a> is the most efficient form of transportation, attaining the equivalent of 700 mpg. <a href="Motor Scooters">Motor scooters</a> get 80 mpg. <a href="Hybrids">Hybrids</a> such as the Toyota Prius get between 40 mpg and 50 mpg. Most American cars range between 20 and 30 mpg, but Americans have a love for <a href="Big Cars">big cars</a> that get lousy mileage. And the absolute record for low gas mileage must go to the <a href="Bagger 288">Bagger 288</a> that is used to dig coal. It gets about 0.0007 mpg!<br>We burn so much energy in transportation because we spend most of the energy transporting the machinery, not the people. A typical American car weighs over 3,000 pounds, of which only 6% is the actual human cargo. In other words, 94% of the energy we use for our cars is completely wasted.<br>Reducing the weight of cars is the obvious solution, but that raises <a href="Automobile Safety">safety questions</a>. Still, we can get by without most of the 2-ton dinosaurs lumbering down our roads, and we don't need four-passenger cars for one-passenger commutes. In fact, millions of people all over the world are doing just fine with <a href="Tiny Cars">very small cars</a>.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">Then there are the high-tech cars of the future: <a href="Electric Cars">electric cars</a>, which have actually been around for a long time, and <a href="Hydrogen Cars">hydrogen cars</a>.]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:KeepOnTruckin%27.jpg">Keep On Truckin'</a><br/><a href="http://www.streetsblog.org/wp-content/uploads/2006/10/IMG_0540_lane_inside_parkedcars.jpg">bike lane</a><br/><a href="http://www.extreme-scooters.com/04images/tank-blue-lg.jpg">motor scooter</a><br/><a href="http://www.autofanclub.info/wp-content/uploads/2011/07/1309970715-42.jpg">Prius</a><br/><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:GP10_diesel-electric_locomotive.jpg">locomotive</a><br/><a href="http://photocarsonline.com/images/20090513162525_2010-nissan-armada-suv-3.jpg">SUV</a><br/><a href="http://www.oto6.fr/6roues/atv/bagger2881.jpg">Bagger</a><br/><a href="http://theinspirationroom.com/daily/print/2008/10/mercedes_crash_test_mammogram.jpg">crash</a><br/><a href="http://www.adelman.com/cars/ev1.jpg">electric car</a><br/><a href="link">hydrogen car</a><br/>]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="Exajoule">
		<Text><![CDATA[<p style="font-size:110%">An exajoule is a whole lotta energy. More precisely, an exajoule is 1,000,000,000,000,000,000 joules.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">Great. What's a joule?</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">A joule is a small amount of energy. Picking a book up off the floor takes roughly one joule of energy. A large incandescent light bulb uses about 100 joules every second. Accelerating a car from 0 to 60 mph requires about half a million joules. One gallon of gasoline contains about 130 million joules.<p>
<p style="font-size:110%">So what does the "exa" mean? Think in terms of memory storage on your computer. One byte is, well, one byte. A kilobyte is a thousand bytes. A megabyte is a million bytes – most digital photos take a few megabytes. A gigabyte is a billion bytes – most computers have a few gigabytes of RAM. A terabyte is a trillion bytes – most computers have maybe a terabyte of hard disk storage. A petabyte is a quadrillion bytes – about as much as a thousand big hard drives can store. And an exabyte is a quintillion bytes – it would take a million big hard drives to store that much data. So an exajoule is a quintillion joules. Not as much as a gazillion joules, but that's still a lot of joules.<p>
<p style="font-size:110%">Oh, and why do we call this unit of energy a "joule"? It's named after James Prescott Joule, the old fart in the picture. He was an English physicist who did some research in thermodynamics. Aren't you glad that it wasn't named after Subrahmanyan Chandrasekhar, who was actually a better physicist? Can you imagine how big a gigachandrasekhar would be?<p>]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[<a href="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/0/0f/Joule_James_sitting.jpg">photo of James Joule</a><br/>]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="Fracking">
		<Text><![CDATA[<p style="font-size:110%">Natural gas is trapped in rocks deep underground. It's a fossil fuel like oil and coal, coming from the same sources that generated oil and coal. Sometimes it's mixed in with oil, and so when we drill the oil, we get the natural gas as a bonus. That's how we've gotten all our natural gas in the past.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">But those methods only reach a small fraction of the natural gas in the ground. There's lots more spread thinly through vast rock formations. It's not worthwhile to drill a well for it, because we only get the natural gas that's close to the well. Isn't that sad? Boo-hoo.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">But wait! There's another way! Suppose we drill a well down for a ways, then drill sideways into a long horizontal layer of rock containing thinly-spread natural gas. Then we pump water down into the well and suddenly compress the water to very high pressures. The high pressure fractures the rock for some distance from the well, freeing up lots more natural gas, which then comes up to the surface. Fracturing the rock this way is called <i>fracking</i></p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">The amount of natural gas we can get by fracking is enormous: the biggest shale formation in the US, the Marcellus formation underneath Pennsylvania and West Virginia, is estimated to hold about 15 trillion gallons of gasoline worth of energy — that's more than ten times as much as all the oil used in the world each year.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">There are three problems with fracking. First, it uses a lot of water: a typical well will require perhaps 400,000 gallons of water. This is not a problem in water-rich places like Pennsylvania, but in the western states, where water is scarce, this is more problematic. The water doesn't come back up, so we can't reuse it.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">Another problem with fracking is the possibility that it will contaminate underground water supplies. At this time, there is no proof that such contamination happens – but that doesn't mean much, because it can take decades for the contaminated water used for fracking seeps into water wells. If, thirty years from now, Grandpa Joe's water well is ruined by fracking taking place today, who does Grandpa Joe sue? The company that did the fracking made its money and could be out of business.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">The third problem with fracking is that we really don't know how much of that natural gas we can really get using fracking. Some rocks are so hard that fracking doesn't free up much natural gas; some of the natural gas is really deep. There's a big difference between what we think is down there and what we can actually get our grubby little hands on.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">Fracking can also be used to improve the yield from oil wells and even revives old, low-yield water wells. Of course, they don't use nasty chemicals when fracking water wells; they use regular water, which isn't as efficient but is clean and safe.</p>
		]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hydraulic_fracturing">Wikipedia on fracking</a><br>
		<a href="http://online.wsj.com/article/SB10001424052970204528204577009930222847246.html">Wall Street Journal on fracking</a><br>
		<a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dZe1AeH0Qz8&feature=player_embedded">a YouTube video about fracking</a><br>
		<a href="http://www.epa.gov/hydraulicfracture/">The Environmental Protection Agency on fracking</a><br>
		<a href="http://www.hydraulicfracturing.com/Pages/information.aspx">a whole website touting fracking</a><br>
		<a href="http://www.slate.com/articles/health_and_science/future_tense/2011/12/is_there_really_100_years_worth_of_natural_gas_beneath_the_united_states_.html">an article that's skeptical about how much natural gas we can get from fracking<br><br><br><br><br><br><br><br>diagram from EPA]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="Free Markets">
		<Text><![CDATA[<p style="font-size:110%">Overall, the free market is the best way to sort out how best to allocate resources (in other words, spend money) and provide them to people. For example, suppose that your neighbor likes to drive a big gas-hog SUV. That thing really burns up gasoline! We're tempted to condemn people like that for wasting energy. But wait a minute: can you really say that you only use gasoline for trips that are absolutely necessary? Have you ever taken a ride in the country just for fun? Do you take the car to go shopping not because you need to buy food, but because you just enjoy shopping? If you use gasoline for frivolous activities, how can you condemn somebody else for doing the same thing? We <b>all</b> do it!</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">You could defend yourself by saying that your activities aren't as frivolous as the next guy's — but who's to say what's really frivolous and what's not so frivolous? Do we want laws saying that driving SUVs is frivolous, but going to football games isn't? That's just not fair.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">There's a better way to sort this out: the price mechanism. If gasoline costs money, then people will decide for themselves how much money they're willing to spend on those "frivolous" activities. You may decide that using gasoline to drive an SUV is frivolous, and so you wouldn't spend the money to do so. But your neighbor has different values and decides that it's worth the money. That way, you get to do what's important to you, and your neighbors get to do what's important to them. Everybody wins, right?</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">The system balances out nicely because, if people want more gasoline, then they'll be willing to pay a higher price for it. That higher price will motivate oil companies to drill more wells and produce more gasoline for everybody. It all fits together neatly and everybody comes out ahead – right?</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">Not so fast. There are a few problems with this way of thinking. The first arises from externalities: the price you pay at the pump doesn't reflect the true cost of the gasoline. For example, when we burn gasoline, we release polluting gases like NOx that damage property and inflict tiny amounts of lung damage on large numbers of people. Scientists have shown that the pollution from cars causes some people to die from asthma, emphysema, and lung cancer. But the lady driving the SUV doesn't pay for those people's medical bills, and neither do you. They get stuck with the costs of <u>your</u> burning gasoline. That's not fair, is it?</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">Here's another problem: there's only so much oil in the ground. Since there's a limited supply, selling oil is like an auction. Each person decides how much they're willing to pay for the oil and 'bids' for the oil by buying it at that price, and we divvy up the oil based on people's 'bids'. That sounds fair, doesn't it? Sure – so long as everybody has a fair chance to bid. With gas stations all over the place, it sure looks as if everybody does have a fair chance to bid, right?</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">But what about the people who aren't here yet? What about your children who haven't been born yet? They're not here yet, so they can't bid on the oil. All we 2013 people are bidding for the same oil that the people in 2060 will want to use. But those people aren't here, so they don't get a fair chance to make their bids. Suppose that they had agents representing them, agents who bid today on oil for use in the future. Those agents would make higher bids, which would drive up the price for us. Since those agents aren't here, we're all paying less for gasoline than we would if the free market were truly fair. Which means we're burning it up faster that we would if everything were fair.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">Here's another example of how free markets don't always work well: <i>efficient</i> markets aren't the same as <i>perfect</i> markets. A perfect market is one in which there's so much competition that every seller has to keep his prices down to the absolute minimum. The opposite of a perfect market is a monopoly. If only one company is selling something that everybody wants, that company can charge exorbitant prices and people just have to pay what that company demands. Monopolies are bad for the economy and they're unfair, so we have laws against monopolies.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">On the other hand, perfect markets divide everything up so that only little companies do the selling. That forces companies to stay small, but often times big companies are more efficient than little companies. Big companies can afford the huge investments required for modern technologies that allow us to tap into larger supplies of oil. A single deep-sea ocean rig can cost $4 billion; only big oil companies can afford that kind of equipment. If we had a perfect market for oil, then there wouldn't be any companies big enough to purchase deep-sea drilling rigs, and there'd be less oil for everybody.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">There's no simple way to trade off the benefits of perfect markets against the benefits of efficient markets. We just have to compromise one against the other, because free markets don't always work the way we want them to.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">These big companies create a new problem called <i>moral hazard</i>. This happens in financial markets where huge companies are so critical to the economy that they know that the government won't permit them to go bankrupt. Knowing that they won't have to pay the costs of huge mistakes, they take big risks, risks that pay off handsomely most of the time (making the bankers rich) – and when the risks fail, costing hundreds of billions of dollars, the government will bail them out. This is exactly what happened in the fall of 2008, when the American financial system nearly collapsed because of foolish risks taken by huge financial institutions like banks. The taxpayers had to bail them out to prevent even greater losses.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">I'm not saying that we should give up on free markets; they're still the best overall way to deal with these problems. But we shouldn't have blind faith in free markets: like everything else, they're imperfect and in some cases they don't work well. In those cases, it's possible for one group of people to cheat another group of people out of billions of dollars.</p>]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Free_market">good article at Wikipedia on free markets</a><br>
		<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Market_failure">another article at Wikipedia on how markets can screw up</a><br>
		<a href="http://miltonfriedman.blogspot.com/"><b>Free to Choose</b>, an excellent documentary on the benefits of free markets</a><br>
		<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Free-Choose-Statement-Milton-Friedman/dp/0156334607">the <b>Free to Choose</b> book</a><br>
		<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Globalization-Paradox-Democracy-Future-Economy/dp/0393071618/ref=sr_1_2?s=books&ie=UTF8&qid=1324233405&sr=1-2">a heavy-duty book on some nasty trade-offs in globalization</a><br>
		<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Late-2000s_financial_crisis">Wikipedia explains the financial collapse of 2008</a><br>
		<a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=_SdtoKeFTi0">A YouTube video on moral hazard</a><br><br><br><br><br><br><br><br>
		<a href="http://www.romanticparishotel.com/wp-content/uploads/2010/09/3-marche-fontaine-aux-innocents-john-james-chalon-1822-">market scene</a>]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="Fusion Energy">
		<Text><![CDATA[<p style="font-size:110%">For decades, the dream of fusion energy has excited scientists, because the basic fuel for fusion energy is the hydrogen in water – and the water in our oceans could provide immense amounts of power for millions of years. As far as we're concerned, fusion is an infinite source of energy. All we have to do is get it working.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">That, it turns out, is not so easy. It's one thing to build an H-bomb, which uses fusion to blow things up. To control fusion reactions, however, is immensely more difficult. The basic problem is that fusion requires temperatures of millions of degrees. What kind of container can hold anything that hot?</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">The first idea was called a <i>magnetic bottle</i>. The idea is to set up magnetic fields that confine the superhot plasma. It works because plasma – the superheated stuff that the sun is made of, and which is necessary for fusion reactions – is strongly affected by magnetic fields, and so a magnetic bottle will definitely hold plasma. The catch is that it's a two-way street: not only do magnetic fields strongly affect plasma, but plasma strongly affects magnetic fields. Which means that, once you set up your magnetic bottle with plasma inside it, the movements of the plasma deform the magnetic bottle, which cause the plasma to move, which deforms the magnetic bottle even more, and so on until the magnetic bottle breaks down. Scientists spent years trying to fix this problem, and they could never get it working. The problem is so difficult that they even gave it a difficult name: <i>magnetohydrodynamics</i>.<p>
<p style="font-size:110%">The next big idea was a Russian one, called <i>Tokamak</i>. The basic idea is to set up a magnetic bottle shaped liked a donut. The plasma could move around in a circle inside the magnetic donut. The plan was to keep the plasma so busy running around inside the donut that it would never try to get outside the donut. They came close, but they could never get it working right.<p>
<p style="font-size:110%">The next big idea is really cool. We start with a tiny little droplet of fusion fuel at the top of a big hollow steel sphere. We drop it and it falls downward. The instant it reaches the precise center of the sphere, we blast it with a bunch of super high power lasers that raise its temperature up to the millions of degrees necessary to fusion to begin. All those fusion reactions generate energy. The idea is to have a steady stream of these droplets getting blasted many times per second, releasing lots of energy. The problem is that the super high power lasers require almost as much energy as the fusion reactions release. Plus there are problems keeping the equipment working for a long time when there are millions of tiny H-bomb explosions going on inside. They've been working on getting it right for 30 years now and someday – someday – they might get it working right. Don't hold your breath.<p>
<p style="font-size:110%">There are some even wilder ideas for fusion power, but none of them have even gotten to the experimental stage.<p>]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="Gaia Hypothesis">
		<Text><![CDATA[<p style="font-size:110%"><i>Symbiosis</i> is the constructive interaction between two or more species. For example, the clownfish (Nemo was a clownfish) has a symbiotic relationship with the sea anemone. The clownfish eats little bugs that eat the anemone, and the anemone's stingers, to which the clownfish is immune, protect the clownfish from predators. Together, the two species are better off than alone.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">There are plenty of similar examples of symbiosis in the biosphere. But why should the concept of symbiosis be limited to just two species acting together? Deep inside your gut, loads of different bacteria help you digest your food. If you eat bad food containing a nasty bacterium such as Escherichia coli, that bacterium will mess up the delicate balance inside your gut and your digestive system will malfunction, leading to what we call <i>food poisoning</i>. Not fun.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">If many different species can interact in complex fashion, why can't <b>everything</b> interact symbiotically? That is, do all the living things on this planet interact symbiotically? Do all species work together for their mutual benefit?</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">Obviously many species don't help each other, they hurt each other. Mice probably don't consider cats to be their benefactors, and grass probably doesn't appreciate the attentions of cattle. But there are also lots of constructive interactions. All the plants on the planet emit oxygen; if there were too much oxygen, then eventually huge forest fires would burn all the plants. Animals convert oxygen into carbon dioxide, which the plants need for their own chemistry. Thus, plants and animals together enjoy a mutually beneficial symbiotic relationship.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">The Gaia Hypothesis claims that the biosphere is symbiotic on a huge scale. This is controversial for a number of reasons. First, it's obvious that, because of predation (creatures eating other creatures), symbiosis is only partial. Of course, the oxygen-carbon dioxide relationship between plants and animals also demonstrates some degree of symbiosis. So the controversy turns over <b>how much</b> symbiosis exists at the planetary level.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">The second portion of the controversy is due to an unfortunate misunderstanding. It's best understood by comparison with evolution theory. When we trace the evolution of a species such as our own, it's all too easy to see purposefulness in the progression. Over millions of years, hominids grew more and more intelligent; was this because somebody (Mother Nature? God? Aliens?) was directing the course of evolution? Of course not! We know that this progress was really just a long sequence of perfectly natural adaptations to changing environments. But it certainly is easy to imagine a guiding hand in the process.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">In the same fashion, some people have interpreted the Gaia Hypothesis to mean that some guiding intelligence (the goddess Gaia?) guides all living things so that they cooperate with each other to keep the biosphere healthy. This is fantasy. The Gaia Hypothesis does not assume any guiding purpose; it instead posits high-level symbiosis that helps keep the biosphere healthy. The mechanisms of this symbiosis are just as unknown to us now as genetics was to Charles Darwin.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">It's true that some New Age mystics misrepresent the Gaia Hypothesis as scientific proof of their worldview; the fact that they do does not discredit the Gaia Hypothesis.</p>]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Gaia-New-Look-Life-Earth/dp/0192862189/ref=pd_sim_b_5">a nontechnical book about the Gaia Hypothesis</a><br/>
		<a href="http://www.amazon.com/The-Ages-Gaia-Biography-Commonwealth/dp/0393312399/ref=pd_sim_b_2">a more technical book about the Gaia Hypothesis</a><br/>
		<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Symbiotic-Planet-New-Look-Evolution/dp/0465072720/ref=pd_sim_b_4">a third book on Gaia</a><br/>
		<a href="http://www.gaiatheory.org/">a website about the Gaia Hypothesis</a><br/>
		]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="Generation III Reactor Tech">
		<Text><![CDATA[<p style="font-size:110%">Almost all of the nuclear power plants currently in use are <i>Generation II</i> reactors. They were designed in the 1960s and 1970s, based on the experience gained from the first research reactors in the 1950s. Generation II reactors have racked up about 15,000 reactor-years of experience, and during that time they have amassed a fairly good safety record.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">The first major accident of a Generation II reactor was at Three Mile Island in 1979, and the safety systems did their job: no significant amount of radioactivity was released and, thirty years later, there is no evidence of any harm to the public ever occurring. The accident at Chernobyl was a very serious accident, but that reactor did not conform to any of the safety standards used in the Western countries. The most serious accident at a Generation II reactor was the Fukushima accident. We still don't have solid data, but the evidence so far is that the total amount of radioactivity released was significant enough to cause perhaps a few hundred cases of cancer in the Japanese population.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">Engineers have used the experience of the last 40 years to design a new generation of reactors. This generation, called <i>Generation III</i> is not radically different from the previous generation. The reactors are still <i>light water reactors</i> using water to transport heat from a reactor to generate heat to drive a turbine. The differences lie in a large number of refinements in the entire system. For example, engineers have developed advanced computer sensor systems that spot trouble sooner and give operators a clearer idea of conditions inside the reactor. Every aspect of the safety systems has been beefed up, from larger, thicker concrete foundations to contain melted fuel, to larger pumps for getting more water into the reactor, to more precise positioning of the control rods, to better protection against false alarms, which tend to make the operators less responsive to real accidents.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">Basically, the difference between Generation III and Generation II is analogous to the difference between the engine in a modern car and the engine in a Volkswagen Beetle. It's still the same basic design, but there's a lot more stuff in there to provide higher efficiency and greater safety.</p>]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="Generation IV Reactor Tech">
		<Text><![CDATA[<p style="font-size:110%">This is the snazzy, high-tech version of nuclear power. It includes a number of technologies, all of which promise big advances over current nuclear power technology. Here are a few of the many ideas under development:</p>
<p style="font-size:110%"><b>Fast neutrons:</b> The neutrons that are created in nuclear reactions move very fast, so fast that they tend to zoom right by uranium nuclei before they can react with it. All commercial power plants therefore rely on <i>moderators</i> to slow down the neutrons coming out of the nuclear reactions. These slower neutrons are more efficient at triggering nuclear reactions. However, they tend to ignore the other radioactive nasty stuff in the fuel, and so the nuclear waste coming out of commercial power reactors is nasty. Fast neutrons aren't as good at triggering uranium reactions, but they're very good at clobbering all the nasty stuff that makes up nuclear waste. Therefore, if we eliminate the moderator and use fast neutrons instead of slow neutrons, the radioactive waste we end up with is much cleaner. In addition, fast neutrons are necessary for <a href="Breeder Reactor">breeder reactors</a>. Therefore, many Generation IV reactor designs use fast neutrons.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">As always, there's a catch. We must compensate for the fact that the fast neutrons aren't as efficient at triggering uranium nuclear reactions. The best way to do this is to concentrate the fuel more densely. However, when the nuclear fuel is concentrated more densely, the reactor is trickier to operate and could – theoretically – blow up like a nuclear bomb if things went horribly wrong.<p>
<p style="font-size:110%"><b>Sodium coolant:</b> Sodium in its pure form is a metal that melts at low temperatures. It has higher <a href="Heat Capacity">heat capacity</a> than water and is therefore much better at soaking up lots of heat, so it makes a wonderful coolant. Even better, sodium doesn't slow down neutrons the way that water does, so it's good for reactors with fast neutrons. There's just one catch: sodium burns fiercely when exposed to water. Even the water vapor in air is sufficient to cause a small fire. Should a sodium-cooled reactor ever suffer a leak or broken pipe, we'll have a fire inside the power plant. That's not good. Of course, sodium-cooled systems are so efficient that they operate at the same pressure your house plumbing works at, so there's less chance of a leak than there is with high-pressure water systems in conventional reactors.<p>
<p style="font-size:110%"><b>Gas coolants:</b> There are a number of designs that use gases to cool the reactor, helium being the most common gas. The advantage of helium is that it is inert: it doesn't pick up any loose radioactivity like water can, and it can't react with anything, so it there wouldn't be any fires. The catch with gases is that they don't hold a lot of heat; to carry away enough heat, they have to be kept at very high pressures, which means that the pipes and under high stress. That's not good.<p>
<p style="font-size:110%"><b>Thorium fuel cycle:</b>It's possible to use thorium as a fuel if we use it in a breeder reactor. That's good on two counts: first, there's lots of thorium to dig up for fuel, and second, the reactions involving thorium never produce anything that could be used for a nuclear bomb.<p>
<p style="font-size:110%">All in all, Generation IV designs are still in the research phase, not the development phase. The earliest date at which we might see such designs in working power plants is 2030 – and that's optimistic.<p>]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[<a href="http://www.world-nuclear.org/info/inf77.html">World Nuclear Association's page on Generation IV reactors</a><br/><a href="http://www.ucsusa.org/assets/documents/nuclear_power/nuclear-power-in-a-warming-world.pdf">The Union of Concerned Scientists report</a><br/><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Generation_IV_reactor">And of course, Wikipedia</a><br/>]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="Geoengineering">
		<Text><![CDATA[<p style="font-size:110%">Let's suppose that the pipe carrying sewage from your toilets broke and began leaking raw sewage into the crawl space under your house. After a week or two, your house would start to smell pretty bad. Now, some people in such circumstances would call a plumber and have it fixed. But let's suppose that you're too cheap to call a plumber, so you come up with a better solution: you buy a crate of air freshener and every day spray the whole house with lots of air freshener. Problem solved, right?</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">A lot of people wouldn't call that much of a solution; other people might call it <i>geoengineering</i></p>.
		<p style="font-size:110%">There are lots of wild schemes for geoengineering approaches to climate change, but two proposals might have some merit. The first is called <a href="Stratospheric Sulfate">stratospheric sulfate injection</a> (dumping a million tons of sulfate compounds into the stratosphere every year), and the second is called <a href="Ocean Fertilization">ocean fertilization</a>.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">Just to show that scientists don't lack imagination, here are some of the other ideas that have been bandied about:</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%"><b>Space sunshades:</b> Let's put huge umbrellas into orbit; they'd block some of the sunlight and help cool the earth!</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%"><b>Ocean foam:</b> All we need to do is mix a few million tons of detergent into the ocean, and all that foam on the ocean's surface would reflect sunlight, helping cool the earth!</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%"><b>Biochar:</b> Start with one ton of organic residues: dead plants, dead trees, dead squirrels – anything that was once alive. Chop it into fine pieces. Carefully heat it in a huge closed pot with no oxygen inside. It will release natural gas that you can capture and use as fuel. When fully cooked, you get a yukky black mess called <i>biochar</i> which is just loaded with carbon. Bury that stuff, and you've removed a lot of carbon from the environment. Repeat several billion times each year and you will have cleaned up some of the carbon dioxide that we emit during that time!</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%"><b>Ocean water inversion:</b> Build a big pipe about 30 feet across and four miles long. Drop it vertically into the ocean so that the bottom rests on the ocean floor and the top is just below the surface. Attach some huge water pumps that pump water from the bottom of the ocean to the surface. That bottom water is very cold and will cool the surface of the ocean. Set up a few thousand more of these pipes and you've made a kind of "ocean air conditioner" to cool the planet! (Batteries not included).</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">As you can see, we're not short of ideas for dealing with climate change. What we're short of is <u>good</u> ideas for dealing with climate change.</p>
		]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Geoengineering">Wikipedia</a><br/><a href="http://www.princeton.edu/~rcai/geoengineering/03_cai_irwin_technical_limitations.html">Nice explanation from Princeton</a><br/><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Whole-Earth-Discipline-Transgenic-Geoengineering/dp/B005DI7RJ6/ref=sr_1_4?s=books&ie=UTF8&qid=1317344391&sr=1-4">a book by Stewart Brand, environmental hotshot</a><br/><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Hack-Planet-Sciences-Nightmare-Catastrophe/dp/047052426X/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&ie=UTF8&qid=1317344530&sr=1-1">another book, more balanced than the one above</a><br/>]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="Glaciers">
		<Text><![CDATA[<p style="font-size:110%">Glaciers are probably the most sensitive indicator of climate change; people noticed that glaciers were shrinking well before we figured out that it was because of climate change. The photograph shows the South Cascade glacier in Washington state; you can see that in just 24 years it has already shrunk quite a bit. Glaciers all over the world are shrinking fast: in the Andes of South America, Mt. Kilimanjaro in Africa, Tajikistan, the Himalayas, Canada, Alaska, Siberia, Montana, New Zealand, Greenland – in fact, glaciers everywhere are shrinking. The biggest loss is in the biggest glacier in the world, called Ilulissat in northwest Greenland. This single glacier puts more ice into the sea than all of the other glaciers of the world combined. It is likely that the iceberg that sank the Titanic came from Ilulissat. In the last 12 years, this glacier has shortened by 12 miles and it is continuing to shorten. At least future Titanics will be safer.</p>]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[<a href="http://ak.water.usgs.gov/glaciology/south_cascade/photos/scg1979_cropped_sm.jpg">glacier</a><br/>]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="Greenhouse Effect">
		<Text><![CDATA[<p style="font-size:110%">Let's put the pieces together now: the earth achieves <a href="Thermal Equilibrium">thermodynamic equilibrium</a> by emitting infrared light into space exactly equal to the amount of heat energy in the sunlight coming into the earth. That infrared light consists of photons that travel through the air. Now we add another tidbit: carbon dioxide molecules absorb infrared photons using the processes described <a href="Absorption">here</a>. So let's imagine an infrared photon emitted from the warm surface of the earth. It flies upward towards space. But lo! It bumps into a carbon dioxide molecule that absorbs it, then re-emits it a split second later. The original photon was heading upwards towards space, but the new photon could be going in any direction. If you think about it, you'll realize that half of the directions are upwards and half are downwards. That means that, if a thousand original photons heading upward towards space collide with a thousand carbon dioxide molecules, then 500 of the newly-emitted photons will end up heading upward and the other 500 newly-emitted photons will end up heading downward – back to the earth.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">Thus, the carbon dioxide acts like an insulating blanket: it reflects some of the heat-carrying infrared photons right back to the earth, so the earth doesn't cool off as quickly. If the earth can't cool off as efficiently, it will retain more heat, which will cause temperatures to rise. This is the greenhouse effect.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">Now there's good news and there's bad news. The good news is that there aren't that many carbon dioxide molecules in the atmosphere, so not many infrared photons get intercepted by carbon dioxide. The bad news is that, by pumping billions of tons of carbon dioxide into the atmosphere, we're increasing the number of carbon dioxide molecules in the air. In the last 50 years we have increased the amount of carbon dioxide in the air by 22%, and the amount of carbon dioxide that we add each year is increasing.<p>
<p style="font-size:110%">But it gets even worse! We haven't talked about the effects of the <a href="Heat Capacity">ocean's heat capacity</a>!<p>]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[<a href="http://www.universetoday.com/wp-content/uploads/2009/09/SED_wall_1920x1200.jpg">earth limb</a><br/>]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="Greenhouse Gases">
		<Text><![CDATA[<p style="font-size:110%">Carbon dioxide isn't the only greenhouse gas; there are actually a bunch of gases that contribute to the greenhouse effect. But only two of these gases are important enough to worry about: water vapor and methane.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">Yep, plain old water vapor is a greenhouse gas. For example, have you ever been in a hot, humid place? Humidity is just the amount of water vapor in the air. Since water vapor is a powerful greenhouse gas, and there's so much of it in the air, it really holds the heat on the surface, and so you don't get a lot of cooling during the night.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">Have you ever spent the night in the desert? If so, you'll know that it gets cold as soon as the sun goes down. That's because there's very little water vapor in the air (deserts are dry, remember?). Without any water vapor, there's nothing to hold back the infrared radiation and the earth cools rapidly. </p>
<p style="font-size:110%">Another example comes when you have a winter storm followed by a clearing. Cold air doesn't hold much water vapor, so the atmosphere has little water vapor to hold back the infrared light from the earth, and when night falls, temperatures plummet. When it's cloudy, you don't feel much temperature difference between day and night, but when it's cold and clear, you can get real cold real fast when the sun goes down.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">Methane is another greenhouse gas. Molecule for molecule, methane is 20 times more powerful in intercepting infrared light than carbon dioxide. The good news is that methane doesn't last long in the atmosphere: the average methane molecule in the air breaks down after ten years or so. The bad news is that it breaks down into carbon dioxide. Gotcha!</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">Where does methane come from? Lots of places. One source is cow burps and farts. Cows make a lot of methane while they're digesting grass, and that methane always comes out in the end – one end or the other.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">Another source of methane is natural gas – in fact, natural gas <b>IS</b> methane. Now, we don't like to waste natural gas, but the fact is that a lot of it leaks out of all the pipes and doodads that we use with natural gas. A lot of it also leaks out during the process of getting it out of the ground. The more natural gas we use, the more leaks into the atmosphere where it only adds to the greenhouse effect. We just can't win for losing, can we?</p>]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="Heat Capacity">
		<Text><![CDATA[<p style="font-size:110%">Here's a simple experiment that you don't really need to do, because you've already done it plenty of times. Heat up a pot of water on the stove almost to boiling. Let it sit for an hour, then stick your finger in the water to see how hot it is. Even after an hour, it's still pretty hot, isn't it? If you heated up a fork or spoon, it would cool off pretty quickly. How is that water can stay hot so long?</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">The answer has to do with something called <i>heat capacity</i>: the amount of heat that something can store. To understand heat capacity, let's think about sponges. First, imagine a really good sponge. You can pour water all over it, and it just soaks up all that water. Compare that with a really lousy sponge: it can't hold as much water. So we can say that sponges have a "water capacity": the amount of water that a sponge can hold.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">Heat capacity is the same thing, only for heat, not water. You "pour heat" into a pan of water and the water soaks up the heat and gets hot slowly. Metal, on the other hand, has low heat capacity, so if you "pour heat" into metal, it heats up quickly. So, to summarize, water can hold a lot of heat without getting much hotter. In the picture we symbolize this with two imaginary test tubes; one has low heat capacity and the other has high heat capacity. If we "pour" the same amount of heat into both test tubes, the temperature in the one with low heat capacity rises more quickly than the temperature in the one with high heat capacity.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">Throw in the fact that the oceans have a LOT of water, and you can see that the earth has, as a whole, a lot of heat capacity. In fact, it has so much heat capacity that, if the sun just died tomorrow and stopped shining, the earth would start to cool – but there's so much heat stored in the oceans that it would take four months for the oceans to freeze!</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">Now let's take the idea of heat capacity and use it with the greenhouse effect in mind. You may recall that I told you that we humans have increased the amount of carbon dioxide in the atmosphere by 22%. Let's suppose that this extra carbon dioxide reduces the amount of heat (infrared radation) leaving the earth by just one-tenth of 1%. So, instead of 200 petawatts of heat leaving the earth, we have only 199.8 petawatts leaving the earth. The difference between the solar input (200 petawatts) and the infrared output (199.8 petawatts) is just 0.2 petawatts. All that heat goes to heating up the earth. Now, if you had a microwave oven with 0.2 petawatts of power, it would heat a gallon of water from ice-cold to boiling in ten billionths of a second. 0.2 petawatts is a lot of power! But the oceans have a lot of heat capacity, and those 0.2 petawatts of power would take 15 years to increase the temperature of the oceans by just 1ºF.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">Think about that. If we increase the amount of carbon dioxide in the atmosphere to increase the temperature by just 1ºF, it would take 15 years before the effect showed up, because the oceans act like a huge shock absorber for heat. We don't feel the shock until 15 years after we've put the carbon dioxide in the air. Which means that things may look OK right now, but if there are going to be any bad consequences for our climate decisions today, we won't experience those repercussions for at least 15 years. It's like driving a truck so big and heavy that it can't slow down very fast. If you see that there's an obstacle in the road ahead and you hit the brakes, the truck slows down so slowly that you'll crash unless you looked very far ahead. That's what we have to do with climate change: look very far ahead.</p>]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[<br/>]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="Heat Pump">
		<Text><![CDATA[
		<p style="font-size:110%">A heat pump is a machine that moves heat from one place to another. Air conditioners are heat pumps; so are refrigerators and deep freezers. Some houses use heat pumps for both heating and cooling.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">The basic operation of a heat pump is fairly simple. We start with the electrical pump at the top center of the diagram. This pump compresses a special gas that's perfect for this job. Now, when you compress a gas, its temperature rises. If you've ever pumped up a bicycle tire, you may have noticed that the nozzel of the pump is hot when you're done. That's because the pump was compressing all the air that went into the tire.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">So the hot, compressed gas flows into a heat exchanger (in red) which is just a bunch of copper tubes. A fan blows air over the copper tubes, which cools the copper tubes, cooling the compressed gas. Now the compressed gas moves on to an expansion valve (bottom center), which permits the gas to expand. When you let a gas expand, it cools. Have you ever sprayed yourself with deoderant and felt how cold it is? The spray is cold because the gas in the spray can is expanding. In the same way, the expanding gas cools as it expands. But it started off cooler than it was when it was compressed (because the fan was cooling it). So when it cools, it gets really cold. The cold gas then moves through the cooling tubes inside your refrigerator, cooling the food. From there it goes back to the compressor pump and the whole cycle starts all over.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">There are a number of tricks you can use to increase the efficiency of a heat pump, such as using a gas the condenses into a liquid when it is cooled and evaporates back into a gas when it is warmed. All these tricks together increase the overall efficiency of a heat pump to as much as 40%. But it still takes energy: electricity is needed to run the compressor motor.</p>]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="Heat Waves">
		<Text><![CDATA[<p style="font-size:110%">You know what a heat wave is; you've probably experienced several in the last few years. In fact, since the year 2000, heat waves have been striking frequently and setting new records all over the world. The United States experienced heat waves in August 2001; April 2002; July and August 2006; June 2008; July 2010; July and August, 2011. The rest of the world has also experienced a series of devastating heat waves during the same period. Not only are heat waves becoming more frequent, they are lasting longer. In times past, a heat wave might last a few days to a week; nowadays, heat waves can drag on for weeks.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">Record-setting temperatures are one way to measure just how serious heat waves can be. In June 2011, 2706 weather stations in the US recorded record high daily temperatures; only 251 set record low daily temperatures. Until 1980, there were just as many high temperature records being set as low temperature records. That makes sense, after all; you expect that, from year to year, you'd have just as many record-setting hot days as record-setting cold days. But since 1980, that hasn't been happening. Over the last ten years, there have been an average of twice as many record high temperatures as record low temperatures – and it's getting worse every year.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">Heat waves kill. Lots of people don't know that they have to drink more water during a heat wave. Lots of old and sick people with weakened constitutions suffer greatly because their bodies can't handle all that extra heat; many die. Heat waves used to kill an average of 400 people every year just in the United States, but that number has been climbing and was over 7000 in 2011. The heat wave in Europe in 2003 killed 35,000 people.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">Heat waves are also expensive. People use a lot more electricity during a heat wave to run their air conditioners. The power company is legally required to have enough power to meet that extra demand for electricity, so it must keep special generators ready to go every day. These are called "peak power plants" and are usually gas turbines. The problem is, they're not used except when it's really hot. That means that these power plants sit idle 90% of the time. The power company still has to pay for them, even though they don't run often. And that extra cost is passed on to you, the customer – which means that you're paying for generators that don't run very often. Most of the electricy you use is cheap to produce – maybe 9¢ per kilowatt-hour. But you probably pay about 12¢ per kilowatt hour. Why the extra charge? Because you have to pay for all the other stuff required to get the power to you: electricity lines, transformers, and all that stuff. Included in those costs is the cost of the power plants that sit idle, waiting for peak demand. Thus, high temperature records cost you money.</p>]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[<a href="http://www.e-forwards.com/wp-content/uploads/2011/07/Heat-Wave-2011-polar-bear.jpeg">hot polar bear</a><br/>]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="High Voltage Direct Current">
		<Text><![CDATA[<p style="font-size:110%">If you read the section on <a href="Transmission Losses">transmission losses</a>, you already know that shipping electricity long distances leads to loss of electricity, and that the best solution to this problem is to go to higher voltages. The problem is, we're talking about, like, half a million volts. Have you ever touched a wire with half a million volts? If you have, then you're dead, and I don't know why you'd be reading this stupid story. Voltages that high can be really tricky to handle safely.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">You know how a spark of static electricity can jump a tiny distance from your finger to something else? Well, a half a million volts can jump across 6 inches of empty air! So building big equipment to handle that kind of voltage is pretty tricky, and as you get closer to a million volts, the problems just become too much; we can't build power lines able to handle a million volts...</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">
		<b>unless</b> we use direct current. Electrical power systems use alternating current (AC), a kind of current that goes back and forth 60 times every second. Direct current (DC) just goes in one direction. Now, at the basic level, the only difference is that AC goes back and forth, like a piston going up and down in an engine, while DC always pushes in one direction, like gravity (well, at least the gravity where I live. Do you live in a place where gravity pushes and pulls alternately? If so, life must be pretty jiggly there.).</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">Anyway, while the difference between the two kinds of current is simple theoretically, it gets to be pretty complicated when you're talking about building circuits for handling a million volts. To make a long story short, you can't do it with AC, but you <b>can</b> do it with DC.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">
		This does require some special new technology to work, but there are already a number of High Voltage Direct Current (HVDC) transmission lines around the country. If we built more of these lines, then we could ship electricity much greater distances without serious loss. The whole country could be tied together in one big grid, enjoying the advantages that arise from pooling all our resources into a single grid.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">The USA has been slow to pick up on HVDC; out of 100 HVDC projects around the world, only 20 are in the US, and many of those are rather puny. The bigtime stuff is being done in Europe; most American HVDC lines use equipment manufactured in Germany.
		<p style="font-size:110%">
		There's an even better way to transmit large amounts of electricity: superconducting wire. If you get wire really, really cold – much colder than the heart of the meanest, nastiest penguin in Antarctica – then it suddenly changes and can conduct huge amounts of electricity without warming up at all. So if we built refrigerated transmission lines, then we could transmit all the power we wanted all over the continent without any power loss at all!</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">The problem is, we're not talking about regular everyday refrigerators. The refrigerators we're talking about compare to the fridge in your kitchen the way that a jet airplane compares to a tricycle. Yep, they cost a lot more. So we can't use superconducting wires yet.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">
		<b>But!</b> Researchers are working hard to come up with special kinds of wires that don't need to be so cold. Every year they do a little better, and someday, they might get them good enough to allow us to build superconducting transmission lines. But don't hold your breath: it won't be anytime soon.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">
		The photo shows high-voltage thyristor valves, which are used to convert the high voltage AC to HVDC and back again.]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[
		<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/High-voltage_direct_current">Wikipedia</a><br/>
		<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_HVDC_projects">Wikipedia list of HVDC projects around the world</a><br/>
		<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thyristor">Wikipedia on thyristors</a><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/>
		<a href="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/1/1c/Manitoba_Hydro-BipoleII_Valve.jpg">thyristor valves</a><br/>]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="How Accurate Is This Game">
		<Text><![CDATA[<p style="font-size:110%">You're probably wondering just how reliable the results of this game are. The short answer is that it's not very accurate at all. The problems that civilization faces with energy, pollution, and climate change are enormously complicated. Even a team of the best scientists and economists wouldn't be able to produce a truly reliable simulation. So how can you trust the work of a yokel wearing a big blue hat?</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">My answer is that this is not meant to be perfectly accurate, it is meant to teach you the first things about the problems we face with energy, pollution, and climate change. After all, in your first science class, did they start off by teaching you quantum electrodynamics? You have to start simple, and this game is a simple introduction to the subject.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">"Simple?!?!?" you snort. "This game is horribly complicated!" Well, yes, that's true: it <b>is</b> too complicated. It's very difficult to master. I had to make tons of agonizing decisions in which I had to choose between making it easier to understand and making it more accurate. I hope I hit the right balance.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">The problem is made worse by the lack of solid data on all the different factors I explored. For example, you'd think that we have lots of good data on exactly how much oil is left in the ground. We don't. I researched this topic extensively, and came up with all sorts of contradictory evidence. I needed to come up with a formula for how much more oil we could get if the price of oil increased. That data really doesn't exist, so I had to make up a formula. I can't prove that my formula is right; all I can say is that I put a lot of research into it and came up with the best I could estimate.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">Then there's the problem of political bias. People disagree on all sorts of important issues. Just how dangerous are nuclear power plants? How much coal is there? How high will temperatures rise if we put a certain amount of carbon dioxide into the atmosphere? There is no agreement on any of these issues. Once again, I did a lot of research and came up with the best numbers I could estimate. I tried hard to be fair to all sides, but I can't guarantee that my numbers are the best.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">I'm proud of the final result. I put a lot of work into the research, into reading lots of different opinions, and on coming up with the best balance between accuracy and simplicity that I could figure out. I know it's not perfect, but I also know that it will help people understand our problems better. I hope you agree after you've played it.</p>]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[<a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=oe4627NmQZg&list=UUFcxwvkvBx4GwyOHHTkB0Aw&index=4">TRUTH</a><br/>]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="Hybrids">
		<Text><![CDATA[<p style="font-size:110%">A hybrid car uses both a gasoline engine and an electric motor to run. There are two advantages to using two completely different kinds of engine</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">The first advantage has to do with the difference between <i>power</i> and <i>torque</i>. Power is how much energy an engine can deliver at its peak power level. Torque is how much force the engine can deliver to the wheels. The trick here is that a gasoline engine delivers its highest power only at high RPMs.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">Suppose that you're waiting at a traffic light and it goes green, so you hit the gas. Your poor little gasoline engine might have 100 horsepower at full speed, but at starting speed like this, it can barely muster 20 horsepower. Sure, its gutsy at high RPMs, but at low RPMs, it's a weakling. That's why cars use transmissions with gears. If the engine were just hooked straight to the axle, then when you were getting started, the engine would be running so slowly that it would simply die.</p> 
		<p style="font-size:110%">So we use gear systems. In first gear, the engine gets to turn many revolutions for each revolution of the axle. That way, the engine can run fast (and so get lots of power) even though the car is going slowly. As the car gains speed, the engine starts going too fast, so you go into second gear, which permits the engine to run more slowly at a given speed. This goes all the way up to fourth or fifth gear, where the engine is turning at its optimal speed when you're on the freeway.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">Electric motors have the opposite ability: they have maximum torque when they're just starting. So even a small electric motor can outperform a larger gasoline engine when it comes to starting from a stop. By combining a gasoline engine with an electric motor, we can use the electric motor for fast initial acceleration, and the gasoline engine for cruising speed. This is more energy-efficient because nowadays we use oversized engines to provide acceptable torque for starting from a stop; by using an electric motor instead, we can use a smaller, more efficient gasoline engine for full speed.<p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">The second advantage of a hybrid is its ability to store and re-use energy. Stop for a moment and think about driving a car in terms of energy rather than speed. You're waiting at a traffic light and it goes green. You hit the gas and the engine starts adding energy to your car, causing it to go faster. Every second, the engine puts more energy into the car, so it goes faster and faster. When you reach cruising speed, you back off on the gas pedal because now you only need enough energy from the engine to make up for the energy lost to friction.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">But when it comes time to stop the car, you have to get rid of all that energy that you built up. So you hit the brakes. The brakes convert your moving energy into heat. That's all they do: convert one form of energy into another form. Since your car has a LOT of energy when its going fast, the brakes have to convert a lot of energy into heat, and they get pretty hot. But they're air-cooled, so they usually stay cool enough to work fine. But if for some reason you were to try to get them to convert too much energy into heat, they'd overheat and stop working. You could do this by loading your car full of lead and then driving down a long steep hill, using the brakes at full speed. That's just too much energy for most brakes to handle.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">Here's where the hybrid does its job. Every electric motor is ALSO an electric generator. If you put electricity into it, it turns. If you force it to turn, then electricity comes out of it. So what if you used electricity to get the car moving, and then, when you want to slow down, reverse the process: use the motor-generator to slow down the car by converting its moving energy back into electricity. If you could do this with perfect efficiency, you'd never need to recharge your battery!</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">Unfortunately, it never gets anywhere near close to perfect efficiency; instead, it operates with net efficiency of only 30% to 40%. But suppose that you're driving in slow traffic, stopping and starting and stopping again. With that kind of traffic, every time you hit the brakes, you're just throwing away energy as heat. But if you're in a hybrid car, nearly 40% of that energy is reclaimed by the generator. That isn't a lot of energy by itself, but if you're doing a lot of starts and stops, the savings add up.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">That's why hyrids get such good mileage. A hybrid with the same performance as a regular gasoline-powered car will get around 50% better gas mileage, depending upon how it's driven.<p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">And if you're wondering why there's a picture of a locomotive, it's because most locomotives are diesel-electric hybrids, only they don't have batteries. The diesel engine makes the electricity that the electric motor uses to move the train. In other words, diesel-electric locomotives rely solely on electricity to move. And you thought that electric vehicles are wimps!<p>]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hybrid_vehicle">Wikipedia on hybrid cars</a><br/>
		<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Diesel-electric_transmission">Wikipedia on diesel-electric systems</a><br/>
		<a href="http://www.hybridcars.com/index.php">a website about hybrid cars of all types</a><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/>
		<a href="http://www.autofanclub.info/wp-content/uploads/2011/07/1309970715-42.jpg">Prius</a><br/><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:GP10_diesel-electric_locomotive.jpg">locomotive</a><br/>]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="Hydrogen Cars">
		<Text><![CDATA[<p style="font-size:110%">There's a lot of excitement about <i>hydrogen cars</i>. These are cars powered by fuel cells that combine hydrogen with oxygen to make electrical power. What's really neat about these is that their emissions consist of water – that's all! No sulfur dioxide, no NOx, no particulates, not even carbon dioxide. Just clean, pure water. Sounds neat, doesn't it?</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">If you haven't already wondered "What's the catch?" then you get ninety lashes with a wet noodle for missing the first law of good environmental understanding. The catch is "Where do you get the hydrogen?" The answer is: "They have to make it from electricity from regular power plants." So, if your electricity comes from coal-burning power plants (and 45% of American electricity comes from such plants), then you're really burning coal to power your car. And coal is a very dirty form of energy.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">In other words, hydrogen is not an energy source, it's an energy storage form. First you use electrical energy to <i>hydrolize</i> water: separate it into hydrogen and oxygen. You then release the oxygen and store the hydrogen in big pressurized tanks. Trucks or pipelines then carry the hydrogen to the gas stations, where you pump it into your car. And your car combines the hydrogen back with oxygen from the air to make water. In other words, we start with water, and we end up with water. </p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">Thus, hydrogen cars do nothing to solve our energy problems. They do, however, replace pollution from cars with pollution from coal-burning power plants.<p>]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[
		<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fuel_cell">Wikipedia on fuel cells</a><br/>
		<a href="http://www.fuelcells.org/">a website devoted to fuel cells</a><br/>
		<a href="http://americanhistory.si.edu/fuelcells/basics.htm">a nicely illustrated site on fuel cells</a><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/>
		<a href="http://www.paenergyfest.com/photos08.shtml">fuel cell car</a><br/>]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="Hyperbolic Cooling Towers">
		<Text><![CDATA[<p style="font-size:110%">These babies are genuinely frigorific technology! (<i>frigorific</i> means "cooling down"). But they're also cool because they're so elegantly simple. We just take warm water that we want to cool and spray it downwards from a height of about 15 feet. Because the spray water is warm, a lot of it evaporates, and the warm air carrying the water vapor rises. It has to rise all the way to the top of the tower before it can get out. Here's the catch: the tower is so high that the atmospheric pressure up there is lower than it is at the bottom of the tower. When you lower the air pressure, it can't hold as much water vapor, so the water vapor must condense into a fog of tiny water droplets – which is exactly the same thing that a cloud is. Now, because the water vapor is condensing, it contracts in volume to 1/1700th of its original volume (just like inside the <a href="Condenser">condenser</a> inside the power plant). Because it shrinks in volume, it lowers the pressure even more, which sucks air up from inside the tower. The only way for more air to enter the tower is through the openings at the base of the tower.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">So a hyperbolic cooling tower is really a huge air pump with no moving parts! It sucks in air at the base, passing it through a shower of warm water where it picks up a lot of water vapor. The air rises to the top of the tower and dumps its water into an artificial cloud. So it's not only a huge air pump, it's also a cloud factory!</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">The catch is that it only works if it's big enough. You can't have dinky hyperbolic cooling towers. Most of these towers are at least 450 feet high. If you make them too small, then the pressure and temperature differences between the top and the bottom are not great enough to insure good air flow.<p>]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:Didcot_power_station_cooling_tower_zootalures.jpg">hyperbolic cooling towers</a><br/>]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="Insulation">
		<Text><![CDATA[<p style="font-size:110%">Every home needs good insulation in the walls and the roof. If your home was built in the last thirty years, it probably has good insulation, but no matter what, you should find out how good the insulation in your house is. The most common type of insulation is batting, a blanket of insulation with a metal foil on one side. If your house does not have much insulation, it's easy to buy some and lay it down in the attic. If the walls of your house aren't insulated, you can't just tear them out and install insulation batting. Instead, it might be possible to use injectible insulation. A contractor drills small holes in the exterior wall and pumps a special fluid into the gap. As the fluid dries, it expands into a solid foam that has good insulating properties.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%"<a href="Measuring Thermal Performance">Here's an experiment</a> you can do to measure just how good the insulation is in your home.</p>]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[<a href="http://www.daviddarling.info/images/batt_insulation.jpg">batting</a><br/><a href="http://www.daviddarling.info/images/cavity_wall_insulation.jpg">insulation</a><br/><a href="http://green-living-made-easy.com/image-files/greeninsulation1.jpg">insulation</a>]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="Light">
		<Text><![CDATA[<p style="font-size:110%">The starting point in understanding climate change is light. There are two simple points to understand: 1) that light is composed of particles called <i>photons</i>, and 2) that each photon has a color.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">1. Photons are the basic "atoms" of light. A beam of light is really just a flood of photons. Photons always travel at the same speed, and you'll NEVER guess the scientific term for that speed. Go ahead, give it a try. I'll wait.</p>

<p style="font-size:110%">OK, have you made your best guess? Here's the answer: the scientific name for the speed of light is <i>"the speed of light"</i>. Isn't that amazing! It's roughly 186,000 miles per second. Photons are teensy-weensy; a beam of sunlight coming in your window will have about 2,000,000,000,000,000,000,001 photons. (The extra photon is for good luck.) Because they are particles, photons can hit atoms or molecules.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">2. Every photon has a color. There are red photons, green photons, blue photons, and yellow photons, and all the colors in between, as shown in the picture. But there are also colors that are invisible to us. For example, a photon can be redder than red, so red that we call it <i>infrared</i>. Our eyes can't see infrared photons. In fact, our eyes can see only a tiny percentage of all the photons out there. Beyond infrared, there are <i>microwave</i> photons, then <i>radio wave</i> photons. On the other side, where photons are more violet than violet, they are called <i>ultraviolet</i>. Beyond ultraviolet there are <i>X-rays</i> and beyond X-rays are <i>gamma rays</i>.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">One other small detail that will come up later: as you can see from the picture, different colors have different frequencies and different wavelengths. For example, pure green light has a frequency of about 600 teraHerz (that's 600,000,000,000,000 vibrations per second) and a wavelength of about half a micrometer (that's 0.0000005 meters).
<p style="font-size:110%">Now that you've got the basics under your belt, you're ready for a new concept: <a href="Thermal Radiation">thermal radiation</a>.</p>]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[<a href="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/c/cf/EM_Spectrum_Properties_edit.svg/1000px-EM_Spectrum_Properties_edit.svg.png">diagram</a><br/>]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="Lighting">
		<Text><![CDATA[<p style="font-size:110%">You can also reduce energy waste by replacing your incandescent light bulbs with compact flourescent light bulbs or with the new high-tech LED lights.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">LED lights get between 100 and 150 lumens of light per watt of power. Flourescent lights come in around 100 lumens per watt, and incandescent lights manage a crummy 20 lumens per watt.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">That's why Congress passed a bill requiring higher efficiencies in light sources. This will have the effect of phasing out interstate sales of incandescent lights over the next ten years.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">Right now, LED lights cost much more than incandescent lights, but let's calculate whether they really save money. We'll compare a 60-watt incandescent light bulb with an LED that produces the same amount of light. The incandescent bulb costs about $1, while the LED costs about $40. The LED lasts about 30 times longer than the bulb, so to compare properly, we need to compare the cost of 30 incandescent bulbs with one LED. Thus, so far the incadescent technology has cost you $30 while the LED technology has cost $40 – the incandescent is ahead by $10!</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">But wait – there's more! One incandescent bulb will burn for about 1,000 hours before burning out, so thirty bulbs will burn for 30,000 hours At a typical price for electricity of $0.10 per kilowatt-hour, that will cost you $180 in electricity. The LED, however, will cost you only about $30 for electricity. Thus, the total cost of using incandescent light bulbs in that 60-watt socket will be about $210, while the equivalent LED will cost you about $70 – one-third the cost of the incandescent bulbs!</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">Some people are angry that Congress passed a law phasing out incandescent light bulbs. They say that they want the freedom to buy whatever kind of light they want. I suppose you could call this "the freedom to do really stupid things". What they forget is the fact that, by wasting electricity, they drive up the price for everybody else.]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[
		<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/LED_lamp">Wikipedia on LED lights</a><br/>
		<a href="http://apps1.eere.energy.gov/buildings/publications/pdfs/ssl/greenbuild2010_mccullough_replacements.pdf">a rather technical PDF on lighting efficiency</a><br/>
		<a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/07/28/technology/28led.html">a good news story about LED lighting</a><br/>
		<a href="http://www.consumersearch.com/light-bulbs/led-light-bulbs">a product review of LED lighting for consumers</a><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/>
		<a href="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/b/b4/Gluehlampe_01_KMJ.png">light bulb</a><br/><a href="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/c/c3/Compact-Fluorescent-Bulb.jpg/544px-Compact-Fluorescent-Bulb.jpg">compact flourescent bulb</a><br/><a href="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/8/84/E27_with_38_LCD.JPG/800px-E27_with_38_LCD.JPG">LED light</a><br/>]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="Limits to Growth">
		<Text><![CDATA[
		<p style="font-size:110%">Why can't we grow solar, wind, and other renewable energy forms as quickly as we'd like? After all, computers, mobile phones, and the Internet have all grown rapidly; why can't we do the same with solar cells?</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">Consider, for example, the growth of personal computers. Over the 30 years from 1980 to 2010, sales grew by an average of about 30% per year. Mobile phone subscriptions increased even faster over the last 15 years, by almost 50% per year. But these are the extreme figures, and they can be attributed to the fact that in each case the technology improved dramatically even as the price was tumbling down. Let's take some more typical cases that are more pertinent. Worldwide electricity use has increased by an average of 4% per year over the last 30 years; worldwide energy use has increased by only 2% per year over the last 40 years.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">There are, of course, many factors that affect the growth rate of an industry: some factors push it up, some factors push it down. But the point I want to make here is that there are factors that can put a ceiling on growth, factors that have nothing to do with technology.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">Suppose that you design a fabulous piece of software that becomes very popular, so that millions of people want it. Selling your software over the Internet is totally automated: you can go from zero sales to a billion bucks overnight. But if you want to sell, say, a videogame in a box, then it takes more time to print all the boxes, make all the CDs, ship them in trucks all over the country, and so forth, so your growth has to be slower.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">Suppose, however, that you want to make solar cells. You need to build a huge (expensive) factory to build them. Once you've got them built, you can't just stick 'em in WalMart and let them sell – no, you need people to install them, whether it's in the home or in big solar parks.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">But you'll need even more. You need experienced executives who know all the ins and outs of the solar cell business, so you don't lose your shirt. You need thousands of managers who know how to organize and lead a team of people who carry out the installations safely. You need inspectors to guarantee the quality of the product and the installation. And there will certainly be lots of government inspectors to make sure that you're not posing a threat to other people. Where are experienced government inspectors going to come from?</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">A big industry spending billions of dollars requires thousands and thousands of people to do all the tasks required to do it safely, quickly, efficiently, and at the lowest cost. You can't just hire kids out of high school to do this work; even college graduates are useless until they've learned the ropes. And when an industry is just getting started, like the solar cell industry, who knows the ropes?</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">I remember, back in the early days of computer games at Atari, nobody knew what they were doing, because nobody had ever done it before. The executives were totally clueless – they'd never even played a game. Those of us who were making games just made things up as we went along. We made all kinds of stupid mistakes, because we were just learning how to make games that were fun. If a games company nowadays were run as shoddily as Atari (and all the other early companies) was run, they'd go broke before they ever got any games done. Nowadays we have thousands of people with years of experience who know how to run a big games operation. But it took 30 years to get from there to here.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">It takes years to build up the army of experienced people necessary to run an industry. You can send software over the Internet in seconds; you can stamp out computer chips in months; but you need years to build up a big community of people who can make an industry go.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">That's one reason why solar energy will never grow as fast as we want it to. In this game, all the energy industries are limited to a maximum growth rate of 20% per year.</p>
		]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="Measuring Thermal Performance">
		<Text><![CDATA[<p style="font-size:110%">Here's how you can measure how good the insulation is in your house. It's a simple test and doesn't give accurate results, but it will give you a rough idea of the overall thermal performance of your house.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">You'll need at least one thermometer, but two are better. You'll also need a cold evening. This experiment works only if you have forced-air central heating (in other words, a furnace or heat pump somewhere that heats air and blows it out of <i>registers</i> on the floor, or sometimes the walls, all over the house.)</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">First determine the heat output of your heater. On the outside of the heater there should be a little notice describing the heater and somewhere the magic words "(number) BTU/hr". The (number) will tell you how many BTU's (never mind what a BTU is, we don't need it) of heat that your heater pumps into the house every hour.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">Now select a nice cold night when you will be slaving away at hours of homework just like you do every night. A cloudy night will give better results than a clear night. Select one of the heat registers; you can use any register in the house, but the one where you do all that onerous homework will be best. Tie onto one of the bars on the heat register something easy to see and light in weight – maybe just a bit of paper on a string. If you do it correctly it will flutter when the hot air is coming out and lay flat when it's not.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">Now place your thermometer someplace in that room where it's not near any heat registers or light bulbs; you want to get a fair measure of the actual temperature in the house.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">Lastly, take a piece of paper and draw two columns on it: the first marked marked "On" and the second labeled "Off". Write down the time that you start collecting data.</p>		
		<p style="font-size:110%">Set an alarm to go off every ten minutes – you can use a kitchen cooking timer or your cell phone or computer. (If you want even more accurate data, set the timer for five minutes.) Whenever the alarm goes off, look at the heat register: is the little flag fluttering? If it is, make a check mark in "On" column on a piece of paper; if it's not, make a check mark in the "Off" column.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">Halfway through the experiment, write down the temperature on your thermometer and then take it outside and put it in a safe place at least three feet away from the house. Leave it there so it can measure the outside temperature.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">Continue the experiment for at least two hours; the longer it runs, the more accurate the data you'll get. When it's time to quit, go outside and read the temperature on the thermometer, then come inside and write that down on your data sheet, along with the time you stopped taking data.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%"><b>Analysis</b> Whenever you have an hour or so to analyze the data, sit down with the data sheet. Count how many times the heater was on and how many times it was off. Calculate the fraction of the time that the heater was on – it's the number of times it was on divided by the total number of measurements you took. For example, suppose that I counted it as "On" 9 times and counted it as "Off" 6 times, then I get the fraction 9/15 or 0.60 as my answer.</p>		
		<p style="font-size:110%">Now multiply that fraction by the number of BTU's per hour on your heater. That tells you how many BTUs your heater generated during the experiment. In my example, if the heater is 100,000 BTU/hr, then the heater generated 60,000 BTU/hr, on average. That's how much heat escaped from your house every hour. Think about it: if your heater had to put 60,000 BTUs into your house every hour just to maintain the temperature, then 60,000 BTUs must have been leaking out of your house every hour. If you're confused by this, try reading about <a href="Thermal Equilibrium">thermal equilibrium</a>.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">The answer you get is the number of BTU's per hour that were leaking out of your house. But we still have to take into consideration the fact that more heat escapes on really cold nights than on normally cold nights.</p>		
		<p style="font-size:110%">To do that, you first subtract the temperature outside from the temperature inside. So in our example, if the outside temperature was 48ºF, and the inside temperature was 68ºF, you'll get a temperature difference of 20ºF. Divide the number of BTUs per hour by the temperature difference. In our example, I divide 60,000 BTUs per hour by 20ºF to get an answer of 3,000 BTUs per hour per ºF.</p>		
		<p style="font-size:110%">But we STILL haven't taken everything into account. We must also consider the fact that bigger houses have more surface area to leak out of; it wouldn't be fair to compare a huge house with a tiny house. So we have to figure out how much area there was for the heat to leak through. Unfortunately, there's no easy and accurate way to do this. Here is one simple way: find out how many square feet your house is. Most people already know that number for their houses.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">Another way is to measure the length of the house and the width of the house. Most houses don't have simple shapes, so you'll have to fudge to get a decent approximate estimate of the length and width. Now multiply the length by the width to get the number of square feet of floor area in your house. For our example, let's say that the house is small and has 1,000 square feet of area</p>		
		<p style="font-size:110%">Now multiply the floor area of your house by 5; that'll get you a VERY rough estimate of the surface area of your house. This only works if your house is a perfect cube, but it's about the best we can do without getting really complicated. For our example, I get 5,000 square feet</p>		
		<p style="font-size:110%">Now at last you are ready to calculate your final result. Divide [the number of BTUs per hour per ºF] by [the surface area of your house]. In my example, I got 2,000 BTUs per hour per ºF divided by 5,000 square feet, so my final answer was 0.4 BTUs per hour per ºF per square foot.</p>		
		<p style="font-size:110%">Is that a good number or a bad number? Here's a way to compare the average insulation value that you got for your house to some other numbers:</p>		
		motionless air: 0.5 BTUs per hour per ºF per square foot<br/></p>		
		insulation: 0.8 BTUs per hour per ºF per square foot<br/>
		wood: about 2 BTUs per hour per ºF per square foot<br/>
		cement: 6 BTUs per hour per ºF per square foot<br/>
		glass: 22 BTUs per hour per ºF per square foot<br/>
		soil: 30 BTUs per hour per ºF per square foot<br/>
		copper: 8,000 BTUs per hour per ºF per square foot<br/>]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="Motor Scooters">
		<Text><![CDATA[<p style="font-size:110%">Motor scooters have always been popular all over the world, and they have been gaining popularity in America over the last ten years. As gasoline prices have soared, motor scooter sales have soared as well.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">It's easy to understand why: motor scooters are fun, easy to use, and they get great mileage.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">The standard motor scooter used the world over has a two-stroke 50cc engine, a top speed of about 35 mph, and boasts a gas mileage of about 80 mpg. Nowadays there are also much larger motor scooters with bigger engines, higher top speeds, and poorer gas mileage. They are meant for a single rider but can carry a second one at a lower top speed.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">These machines are great for short trips on urban or suburban streets where the speed limit is 35 mph. They can be parked almost as easily as a bicycle, and in fact on many college campuses there's a place for parking scooters right next to the bicycle racks.<p>
<p style="font-size:110%">Motor scooters fall between mopeds (bicycles with tiny engines that require the rider to provide some of the power by pedaling) and motorcycles, which are much bigger, heavier, more powerful, faster – and get gas mileage barely better than a car. Most of the recent boom has been in motor scooters rather than mopeds or motorcycles.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">People worry about how safe it is to drive a motor scooter. No doubt about it, crashing a motor scooter is a lot more dangerous than crashing a car, because you're out there in the open, unprotected. However, there is nothing intrinsically dangerous about motor scooters or motorcycles: an experienced and careful rider is every bit as safe as the driver of a car. It's true that you must be more careful on a scooter than in a car, but if you are careful, the chances of getting hurt are microscopic.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">Here are the main reasons why people get hurt riding motor scooters:</p>
<p style="font-size:110%"><b>No helmet</b> You've got to be brainless to ride without a helmet – and you'll certainly be brainless soon enough.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%"><b>DUI</b> Guess what? Driving under the influence of alcohol or drugs is even more dangerous on a scooter than in a car, because you can't fall over and break your leg in a car.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%"><b>Trusting car drivers</b> The only state of mind that works while driving a scooter is paranoia. You have to assume that you are completely invisible or that every car on the road is out to run you down. "Defensive driving" has to be an understatement while driving a scooter.</p>

<p style="font-size:110%"><b>Driving while young</b> Youngsters love to ride on scooters, and youngsters are the most dangerous driving group in the world. What's really scary is the fact that a lot of kids too young to drive cars are allowed by their parents to drive scooters. This is really stupid: a large fraction of injuries on motor scooters are suffered by too-young drivers. Motor scooters don't cause youngsters to have more accidents, they just give them lots more opportunity to make fools of themselves. The upside of this is that idiot youngsters on motor scooters do less damage than idiot youngsters in cars. If you're in your teens and you want to drive a motor scooter, you damn well better grow up the second you sit down on that scooter.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%"><b>Driving while male</b> There's something exhilirating about feeling the wind in your face – and male exhiliration usually leads to male stupidity. One of the reasons that motor scooters have a better safety record than motorcycles is that more women drive motor scooters. If you are a young male and you want to drive a motor scooter or motorcycle, then you must constantly repeat to yourself while driving, "Is today a good day to die?"</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">I drove a small motorcycle during my youth. Starting at age 18, I drove a Honda 160, a small bike with a top speed of maybe 65 mph. I drove that thing all over creation, amassing an astounding 100,000 miles on it, while going through several crankshafts and lots of cylinder replacements. I have replaced almost every part on that bike except the frame. I still have it, and it still runs. More important, *I* still run. In all that driving, my worst accident resulted in only a skinned shin. I had at least two near-misses with bad drivers that would surely have been collisions had I been in a car. That little bike was agile! The monster bikes people ride these days are no more maneuverable than a Cadillac.</p>]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[<a href="http://www.inpraiseofmotorscooters.com/journal/">all about motor scooters</a><br/>
		<a href="http://motorscootermuse.com/scooter_safety.php">motor scooter safety page</a><br/>
		<a href="http://www.scooterfocus.com/scooter_safety.html">another motor scooter safety page</a><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/>
		<a href="http://www.extreme-scooters.com/04images/tank-blue-lg.jpg">motor scooter</a><br/>]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="Nuclear Reactions">
		<Text><![CDATA[<p style="font-size:110%">Nuclear reactions are accomplished through <i>fission</i>, which is just a fancy word for "breaking up". Our story starts with a big fat uranium nucleus. Uranium nuclei are just about the largest nuclei you can find. Now, the nuclei of atoms are like water balloons: they're held together by internal force. Uranium nuclei are like water balloons that have been filled almost to bursting. They're wobbly. If a neutron just happens to hit a uranium nucleus, the impact is enough to break it (just like if you hit an overfilled water balloon with a rock.) When a uranium nucleus breaks – excuse me, <b>fissions</b> – it splits into two big pieces plus three neutrons, plus a <b>lot</b> of energy. </p>
<p style="font-size:110%">That energy ends up as heat. But the real fun comes from those three extra neutrons that get thrown out when the uranium nucleus fissions. They tear off into the wild blue yonder, but if there are other uranium nuclei in the neighborhood, they're likely to hit one or more of those nuclei. When those nuclei fission, they release even <b>more</b> neutrons, which hit more nuclei, and so on and so on until they've split up most of the uranium nuclei. This all happens very fast (like, in a few microseconds), and all that energy being released in a few microseconds makes what we call "a nuclear explosion".</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">But there's a catch to all this: in order for those neutrons to hit other uranium nuclei, those uranium nuclei have to be packed very tightly together to increase the chances of a neutron hitting a nucleus. It turns out that this is very hard to do – which is a good thing, because if it were easy, then anybody could build a nuclear bomb and usually "anybody" means "nasty people". Guess what kind of fun they could have with nuclear bombs?</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">One last thing: does the Second Amendment cover nuclear bombs?</p>]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nuclear_chain_reaction">Wikipedia</a><br/><a href="http://blogs.scientificamerican.com/guest-blog/2011/07/13/natures-nuclear-reactors-the-2-billion-year-old-natural-fission-reactors-in-gabon-western-africa/">Natural nuclear reactors</a><br/><a href="http://www.montereyinstitute.org/courses/AP%20Physics%20B%20II/course%20files/multimedia/lesson54/lessonp.html">a simple video explanation of nuclear reactions</a><br/><a href="http://library.thinkquest.org/17940/texts/fission/fission.html">another nice explanation</a><br/>]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="Nuclear Safety">
		<Text><![CDATA[<p style="font-size:110%">If you turn off a flourescent light, it will continue to glow faintly for a few seconds afterward; it's still releasing energy. A nuclear reactor is exactly the same, except for two things: 1) it releases a <b>lot</b> more energy, and 2) it does so for a lot longer. When you first shut down a nuclear reactor, its power output immediately drops from 3000 megawatts to 200 megawatts. But after a week it's still generating about 6 megawatts of power Which means that you can't just turn off a nuclear reactor. You shut it down and then you wait weeks for it to burn out. During that time you must continue to pump cooling water in to keep it cool. But what happens if there's an accident at the plant that prevents you from pumping cooling water? This is exactly what happened at Three Mile Island in 1979 and at Fukushima Dai-Ichi in 2011. They shut down the reactors with no problem, but they were not able to get enough cooling water to the reactors.<p>
<p style="font-size:110%">This isn't supposed to happen. Every nuclear power plant is equipped with a variety of back-up systems to insure that it can continue to pump cooling water to the reactor core even after an accident. But at both Three Mile Island and Fukushima Dai-Ichi, the backup systems were only partly successful in supply cooling water. In both cases, the reactor cores melted.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">A reactor core contains a humongous amount of nasty radioactive stuff, so it's critical that it not be allowed to escape from inside the plant. Reactors are kept inside large <i>containment structures</i> – great big buildings with thick steel-reinforced concrete walls. The plan is that, no matter how bad things are inside the containment structure, nothing bad will escape. This is exactly what happened at Three Mile Island: the reactor core melted, but the containment structure held it all inside safely and no dangerous levels of radioactive stuff escaped. At Fukushima Dai-Ichi, we're pretty sure that the containment structures mostly held firm, although one of the containment structures probably cracked.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">But there was an even bigger problem with the <a href="Spent Fuel Pools">spent fuel storage</a> at <a href="What Happened at Fukushima">Fukushima Dai-Ichi</a>.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">The accident at <a href="Chernobyl">Chernobyl</a> was completely different in nature, and much worse.</p>]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nuclear_safety">Wikipedia</a><br/>
		<a href="http://www.ucsusa.org/nuclear_power/">an anti-nuclear view</a><br/>
		<a href="http://www.world-nuclear.org/info/inf06.html">a pro-nuclear view</a><br/>
		<a href="http://www.ne.doe.gov/pdffiles/nppsopps.pdf">the Department of Energy's view</a><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/>
		<a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-3PL74S1Oi_Q/TZKBiztkMkI/AAAAAAAABFM/cEA2F2OjIxY/s1600/Homer-Simpson-nuclear-plant.jpg">Homer Simpson</a><br/>]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="Ocean Fertilization">
		<Text><![CDATA[<p style="font-size:110%"><i>Phytoplankton</i> are tiny single-celled creatures that live on the surface of the ocean. Think of them as "teensy-weensy plants in the sea". They react to sunlight by growing in numbers. These phytoplankton are eaten by other microscopic creatures, which in turn are eaten by tiny shrimp, which are eaten by fish, which are eaten by larger fish, which we eat. In other words, phytoplankton sit at the base of the food pyramid in the ocean. Every living thing in the ocean ultimately gets its food from phytoplankton. Obviously, phytoplankton are crucial to the ecology of the ocean.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">Occasionally, however, there can be too much of a good thing. When underwater currents drive sediments from the seafloor up to the surface, phytoplankton can go wild and reproduce like crazy. In such cases, we get huge <i>phytoplankton blooms</i> that cover the ocean for miles in a dense layer of phytoplankton. Eventually the phytoplankton are eaten or die off, and their tiny little bodies sink to the bottom of the ocean, taking with them the carbon that they pulled out of the atmosphere to build their bodies.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">It just so happens that the main thing preventing phytoplankton blooms is the shortage of iron dissolved in the water. Phytoplankton can get everything they need to grow up strong and healthy in plain old seawater – except for iron. There isn't much iron in normal seawater, so phytoplankton blooms usually happen when some underwater currents suck sediment rich in iron up from the seafloor to the surface.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">This means that, if we just add iron to the ocean, we'll get phytoplankton blooms, which will suck lots of carbon dioxide out of the atmosphere and drag it down to the bottom of the ocean, getting rid of it forever (as far as we're concerned).</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">But don't forget the first rule of environmental problems: there's always a catch. There are actually several catches to this idea. First, we really don't know how much carbon dioxide these phytoplankton blooms remove from the atmosphere. Second, sometimes phytoplankton blooms can kill other creatures in the ocean, disrupting the whole ecosystem for a hundred miles – and we aren't sure exactly how to cope with this possibility. However, there's a lot of research going on about this and we might actually figure out a good way to do it.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">The photograph is from a satellite; it shows a phytoplankton bloom a hundred miles across.]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Phytoplankton">Wikipedia on phytoplankton</a><br/><a href="http://www.whoi.edu/oceanus/viewArticle.do?id=34167">long article on all aspects of ocean fertilization</a><br/><a href="http://www.rsmas.miami.edu/pressreleases/20071129-lutz.html">study claiming that ocean fertilization won't work.<a/><br/><a href="http://unesdoc.unesco.org/images/0019/001906/190674e.pdf">a detailed report on ocean fertilization</a><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:Phytoplankton_SoAtlantic_20060215.jpg">label</a><br/><a href="link">Phytoplankton bloom</a><br/>]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="Organic Solar PV Tech">
		<Text><![CDATA[<p style="font-size:110%">All regular solar photovoltaic cells use silicon to convert sunlight into electricity. Silicon is nice, but organic molecules – the same kind of molecules that operate in all living creatures – are more efficient at the molecular level. Solar photovoltaic cells that rely on organic molecules should theoretically be capable of attaining higher efficiences. Scientists have built them in the laboratory, but they're not quite ready for commercialization: they're too expensive and their efficiency is too low.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">What's especially neat about organic solar photocells is that they are extremely thin and can be manufactured in plastic sheets. That means that, once we get them working well enough, we can mass-produce them in huge quantities.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">Even better, because they are in thin plastic sheets, they can be bent without damage. They can be fitted onto any curved surface, which will give them many applications where regular solar cells won't do. </p>
		]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Organic_solar_cell">Wikipedia</a><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><a href="http://www.icis.com/blogs/green-chemicals/screen%20printed%20solar%20cell.jpg">organic solar cell</a><br/>]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="Peak Load Management">
		<Text><![CDATA[<p style="font-size:110%">After reading <a href="Peak Load Versus Base Load">the backgrounder on peak loads</a>, you're probably wondering if there isn't any way to cut the costs arising from peak loads (keeping expensive power plants ready to go but not using them much). There are two particularly interesting solutions</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">
		The first is called <i>peak load management</i>. Suppose that you run a bakery in Phoenix, Arizona. The power company offers you a deal: if you'll let them turn off your ovens by remote control during the hottest parts of the day, they'll lower your electricity rates. That's a great deal, because you probably don't want to be running your ovens on the hottest days anyway. You can schedule your baking for the cooler hours of the early morning and just plan on not using them when it's hot. That's a great deal, isn't it?</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">
		It's also a great deal for the power company. They install a special power meter that has two connections: one to your regular stuff and a special one to your ovens. On a hot day, when they start to get near peak power, they can send an electrical signal down the power lines that will tell every one of those special power meters to turn off its special power line. All over the area, ovens and other electrical devices turn off, reducing the load. That way, the power company doesn't have to have so many extra power plants sitting around twiddling their thumbs, waiting for peak load. That saves everybody money.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">
		However, that's not the only way to use peak load management. Many power companies ask their residential customers to sign up for the same deal, with the power company getting the right to turn off their air conditioning at peak load times. This is a great deal for the power company, because air conditioners are the biggest single contributor to peak demand. But it's a lousy deal for most people, because it means that the power company can shut down your air conditioning at the hottest time of the year. The shutdown will only last a few hours, but it's still bad news for most people.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">
		A second way to handle peak load problems is with a scheme called <i>peak load pricing</i>. The idea is simple and clear: you have to pay the actual cost of the electricity that you use. Electricity during peak load time is more expensive to make (because they're relying on generators that they don't use often), so logically, you should pay more for that electricity. That's exactly what peak load pricing does. They'd install a new kind of electrical meter in your house, one that records not just how much electricity you use, but <b>when</b> you use it. Then they tell you what the prices are at different times of the day. Sometimes it's easier to simply set prices based on the temperature: on really hot days, everybody knows that electricity costs more.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">
		The advantage of peak load pricing is that it's about as fair as you can get. Everybody knows that electricity is more expensive during peak times, so everybody will want to reduce their electricity use during those times – which will lower the demand for electricity during those times, reducing the size of the peak.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">
		There is also a technology for handling peak load problems: <a href="Pumped Storage">pumped storage</a></p>
		]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peak-load_pricing">Wikipedia</a><br/>]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="Peak Load Versus Base Load">
		<Text><![CDATA[<p style="font-size:110%">People want <a href="Variable Demand">different amounts of electricity at different times</a>. The law requires that power companies always supply enough electricity to meet the demand, no matter how much it varies. (After all, the power companies get to have monopolies, and this is part of the deal.) So power companies have to scramble to make sure that there's always enough power on tap to meet the demand of the people. At the same time, they must not make too much power, lest the voltage get too high and burn out every electric device that's turned on. In other words, they are running a system with a maximum level and a minimum level, and the difference between the maximum and the minimum is usually about 10% – and those numbers change steadily throughout the day.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">
		The lowest demand for power is the bottom of the cycle: the lowest amount of electricity that they must generate. That's called <i>base load</i>. That's what they must supply 24 hours a day, 7 days a week, 365 days a year. On the hottest afternoon of the hottest day of the year, they have to supply <i>peak load</i>, which can be a lot more than the base load.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">
		Here's their problem: base load is neat and clean: they just set up power plants big enough to supply the base load, and then let those power plants run all the time. Nuclear power plants are great for this, as are coal-burning power plants.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">
		But for peak load, they have a more difficult problem: they have to have the power plants ready to go all the time, but they don't want to run those other power plants all the time: they want to run them only when the load gets higher than the base load. The problem is made trickier by the fact that <a href="Power Plant Regularity">different power plants have different operating limitations</a>. So what they do is set up a bunch of different power plants, each of which has its own strengths and weaknesses. They operate the nuclear and coal plants 24/7/365 to cover the base load, then bring in natural gas turbines to handle some of the intermediate load, and hydroelectric plants to handle the peak demand. (Some utilities reverse this order, depending on how much hydroelectric power they have to work with.)</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">
		But here's the problem: the peak load power plants (natural gas plants and hydroelectric plants) aren't used all of the time. In fact, sometimes they sit there idly for days on end, not being used at all. These are expensive power plants, and somebody has to pay for them even when they're not actually running. Who do you think ends up paying for them: Santa Claus? Bill Gates? Enron? Nope. It's you and me who foot the bill for these unused power plants. It shows up in our electricity bills. So we end up paying for power plants that aren't used all the time. That's not very efficient, is it? Well, you gotta better idea?</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">
		As a matter of fact, people have come up with <a href="Peak Load Management">two ways to reduce those costs</a>.</p>]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="Peltier Cooler">
		<Text><![CDATA[
		<p style="font-size:110%">A Peltier cooler is a solid state device that moves heat from one of its sides to the other. When it's running, heat moves from the cold side to the hot side. It's an electronic heat pump with no moving parts. Compare this with the <a href="Heat Pump">heat pumps</a> we use for home heating and cooling and refrigerators we use today. They have moving parts: the compressor motor and the pump and the moving gas. They make noise and they break down. But a Peltier cooler has no moving parts, so there's nothing to wear out or break down.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">There is one catch ("There's ALWAYS a catch!"): Peltier coolers are quite inefficient – only about 5% efficient, comparied with the 40% efficiency that mechanical heat pumps can achieve. So right now, Peltier coolers are only useful when you only need to cool something small. There are Peltier refrigerators that you can use while camping, but they eat up a lot of power and they don't get very cold.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">So where's Mr. Science when you need him? Well, he's working on it, but we've got a long way to go before Peltier coolers are efficient enough to replace refrigerators. Don't hold your breath.</p>
		]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="Pigovian Tax">
		<Text><![CDATA[<p style="font-size:110%">Arthur Cedric Pigou was an eminent English economist. How he got that way is anybody's guess, but my best guess is that he was mercilessly taunted by his schoolmates because of his name. Indeed, "pig-oo" is such an unpleasant word to pronounce that economists refer to his most enduring idea as <i>Pigovian</i> taxation, which sounds a little better.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">The basic idea of Pigovian taxation concerns a tricky social problem. Suppose that a factory emits nasty pollution that hurts people: how should we deal with the problem? We can't ignore the damage done by the factory, but at the same time, we don't want to shut down the factory because it makes a useful economic contribution to society. How do we balance these two competing considerations?</p>
<p style="font-size:110%"><b>Regulation:</b> This is the most common approach. Government officials carefully study what reasonable solutions are available, and then require the factory to apply those reasonable solutions. Thus, the trade-off between economic benefits and personal injuries is made by government officials. This solution tends to be clumsy; it's impossible to write up regulations that apply well to every situation, so the regulations we end up with are usually too lenient for some factories and too harsh for others.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%"><b>Tort:</b> This is how most personal injuries are addressed. If you do something that hurts me, I sue you under tort law and, if I can prove that your action really did injure me, then I can demand that you pay me to reimburse me for my injuries. This works just fine when there's a single individual whom we can clearly identify as the victim of the emissions from a factory. But it seldom works with pollution, because it's impossible to identify a single victim. The harm is spread out among many people. Which brings us to:</p>
<p style="font-size:110%"><b>Class action suits: </b>This allows a large group of people (a "class") who have suffered small injuries from a large corporation to sue it collectively, and, if they prevail, collect a big chunk of change that's split up among the members of the class. The problem with class action suits is that lots of the money ends up going to lawyers, and many members of the class never benefit from it. It's ultimately an inefficient system, but it does serve to dissuade large corporations from doing the nasty things that they might get sued for.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%"><b>Cap and Trade</b> This system begins by setting a maximum amount of pollutant that is acceptable: the "cap". The cap is always set to equal the current amount being released. Every company that is releasing the pollutant automatically gets a free license to continue releasing the same amount of pollutant forever. It can sell the license, or parts of it, to other companies. The appeal of cap and trade is that it doesn't hurt industry right now; only when the industry grows does the cap start to pinch. Presumably, the companies releasing the pollutant will install better equipment to reduce their releases, permitting them to sell parts of their licenses to cover the cost of the new equipment. The downside of cap and trade, though, is that it legalizes the current releases of the pollutant, which may already be dangerously high, and it never allows future reductions if we learn that the pollutant is more dangerous than we had thought. </p>
<p style="font-size:110%">As you can see, none of these conventional approaches really does a good job of coping with the pollution problem created by the factory. That's where the Pigovian tax comes in; it's levied on any kind of damage to society or the environment. Take sulfur dioxide, for example. It damages the lungs of people, leading to emphysema and lung cancer. But it also damages the lungs of <b>all</b> creatures: dogs and cats and horses and cows, and vegetation as well: crops and trees and grass. It also damages the surfaces of buildings, corrodes the steel in bridges, and degrades paint. Its effects are widespread but, in isolation, tiny. So we have the government do some research and come up with an estimate of the total damages inflicted upon society by each ton of sulfur dioxide. Then it levies a tax on everybody who releases sulfur dioxide, measured in dollars per ton. You're perfectly free to emit as much sulfur dioxide as you wish, but you have to pay for the damages you inflict upon society.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">There's no reason why a Pigovian tax must precisely equal the amount of damage inflicted by any pollutant. It could be less than the damage, if we felt that the industry creating the pollutant was important. It could be <b>more</b> than the amount of injury done, if we believe that the pollutant we're taxing has effects we just don't like. For example, of somebody emitted a pollutant that killed people's dogs, but did no other damage, we wouldn't just tax them to pay for the cost of the dogs – we'd probably want a much stiffer tax to discourage the release of such a pollutant.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">The value of Pigovian taxes is that, of all the various remedies we can apply to environmental problems, Pigovian taxes are the most closely attuned to fundamental principles of capitalism and the <a href="Free Markets">free market</a>. This is why they are more efficient than any other form of environmental control.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">Besides, doesn't it make sense that you should stock your piggy bank with proceeds from a Pigovian tax? If instead you used an income tax, it would have to be put into an Inky bank, and a sales tax would have to go into a Sally bank.]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pigovian_tax">Wikipedia</a><br/><a href="http://gregmankiw.blogspot.com/2006/10/pigou-club-manifesto.html">The Pigou Club Manifesto</a><br/><a href="http://nopigouclub.blogspot.com/">The NoPigou Club</a><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><a href="http://www.liveinternet.ru/users/kakula/post140940085/">Pigou</a><br/>]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="Poles Vs Equator">
		<Text><![CDATA[<p style="font-size:110%">You may have wondered, "Why does the greenhouse effect cause more warming at the poles than at the equator?" The answer has to do with both water vapor and carbon dioxide. At the equator, there's lots of water vapor in the air (it's really humid at the equator). But at the poles, it's very dry, because cold air cannot hold much water vapor. Since water vapor is a very powerful greenhouse gas, any additional carbon dioxide at the equator will have its effects buried by the much stronger effects of water vapor. So, more carbon dioxide doesn't have much effect at the equator.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">It's a completely different story at the poles. There's almost no water vapor in the air there, so there's no greenhouse effect to speak of. But if you add carbon dioxide to the air there, then it starts producing a greenhouse effect.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">In other words, the greenhouse effect is already pretty much maxed out at the equator, so more carbon dioxide there doesn't have much effect. But there's almost no greenhouse effect at the poles, so even a tiny amount of carbon dioxide has a big effect.</p>]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[<a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-Mctcm4v8U6Q/TacNMUJNJTI/AAAAAAAACT4/ZYKMIkm2l0U/s1600/052_1.jpg">tropical</a><br/><a href="http://www.deshow.net/d/file/travel/2011-02/extraordinary-arctic-landscape-898-2.jpg">polar</a><br/>]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="Poor World People">
		<Text><![CDATA[<p style="font-size:110%">Seven billion people live on this planet; two billion enjoy a comfortable life, never worrying about getting the basics of life. Another two billion are moving out of poverty; but three billion people live on less than $2.50 a day, scratching out a living as best they can.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">They can never be certain that they'll have food to eat in a week's time, they get by with simple clothing and primitive housing. They can count themselves lucky if they have access to clean water. Their neighborhoods often reek of raw sewage because they have no sewage treatment systems. They might have some electricity, and perhaps a neighbor with a cell phone they can use when necessary. Not many of them can read and write.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">In many poor countries, life expectancy is less than 50 years. One in ten babies dies in childbirth. The mother dies in one of every 200 childbirths. Every year, seven million children under the age of 5 die, almost all of them in poor countries. Two-thirds of these people have no toilets or latrines. One billion people have no way to get safe drinking water; millions of them die each year from easily preventable water-borne diseases.</p>]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[<a href="http://www.poverty.com/">website about world poverty</a><br/><a href="http://world-poverty.org/default.aspx">another website about world poverty</a><br/><a href="http://www.globalissues.org/issue/2/causes-of-poverty">and another</a><br/><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Creating-World-Without-Poverty-Capitalism/dp/1586484931">a book by a brilliant economist</a><br/><a href="http://www.glitzypetjewelry.com/">a very special website</a><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><a href="http://www.matercare.org/assets/image-gallery/Photos-from-Kenya/kenya/_resampled/SetWidth500-Kenyan-Family.jpg">Kenyan family</a><br/>]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="Power Plant Regularity">
		<Text><![CDATA[<p style="font-size:110%">Every kind of power plant has its own special needs and capabilities that the people running the grid must take into account.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">
		<b>Nuclear power plants</b> are stubborn: they work best when they run at full power 24/7/365. Once you get a nuclear power plant running at full steam, you either leave it there or you shut it down completely. In fact, one of the mistakes that led to the nuclear accident at <a href="Chernobyl">Chernobyl</a> was that the operators were raising and lowering the power levels of the reactor. That's a no-no.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">
		<b>Coal-burning power plants</b> and <b>oil-burning power plants</b> are more forgiving, but they still work best when you just run them flat out 24 hours a day. Yes, you can raise and lower the power levels, but you can't just do it willy-nilly: you have to bring the power up or down slowly so that the temperatures inside don't change too quickly. With a big power plant like that, sudden changes in temperature can cause pipes to warp, bend, and twist. That's not good.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">
		<b>Natural gas power plants</b> are really good for fast changes. That's because they use a  different turbine system that can more easily go up and down in power.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">
		<b>Hydro-electric power plants (dams with generators)</b> are probably the most flexible of all generating systems. You can turn them on and off in something like a minute.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">
		<b>Solar and wind energy systems</b> have a different problem: you can't control when they go on and off: the weather does! When the sun is out or it's windy, they make lots of electricity. When the sun is down, or when it's cloudy, or when there's no wind, they don't make electricity. This makes life especially difficult for the grid operators, because they have to take the addition of that energy into account into their planning, but they can't control how much or little electricity it makes at any given moment.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">
		Suppose that you're driving a car down the street, and your little brat of a kid has sneakily rigged up a string to the gas pedal and is sitting in the back seat, pulling on the string every now and then. One minute the car is speeding up for no reason, and the next minute it's slowing down for no reason. It would be pretty hard to drive the car, wouldn't it? That's sorta like the problem that grid operators face with solar and wind energy. It's not as bad as the brat with the string, because the ups and downs take place more slowly, and it's possible to get weather data in advance that will warn you about unexpected changes. But it's definitely a headache, and ultimately it imposes its own special costs on electricity.</p>]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="Pumped Storage">
		<Text><![CDATA[<p style="font-size:110%">One of the biggest pains for electricity companies is that you can't store electricity, at least not in any usable amounts. Even big batteries don't store enough energy to make much of an impression on the grid; if we tried to use batteries to make up shortfalls, they'd run out of juice in seconds. This is why peak load is so expensive: power companies can't save electricity to prepare for peak load. They have to be generating it at the instant it's needed.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">But there <b>is</b>, in fact, another way to store electricity, and it's called <i>pumped storage</i>. Suppose you run a power company and you have a dam with a big lake, with generators at the bottom of the dam making electricity. You realize that a generator is also a motor: if you spin the shaft with some force, electricity comes out, and if you put electricity in, it spins by itself.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">In a hydroelectric dam, the water falls into a huge, super-efficient water wheel, forcing it to spin. The water wheel is connected to a generator that makes electricity. But you could just as easily go the other way: use lots of electricity to force the water wheel to turn in the other direction, pumping water back up into the reservoir.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">In other words, when you have extra electricity to spare, you can use it to pump water up into the reservoir. Later, at peak demand time, you can let the water in the reservoir come out, turning the generator and making electricity. In other words, your system saves electricity!</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">As always, there are a few catches. First, you can only pump so much water into the reservoir; pump too much and it spills over the top of the dam. The total amount of water you can store in the reservoir limits how much electricity you can store.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">The second catch is that you have to have a reservoir at the bottom of the dam to hold all the water that you intend to pump up into the upper reservoir. A normal dam just lets the water that comes out flow down the river; you need to save enough water for later use. </p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">The second catch is that about 25% of the energy is lost in each cycle. That's not a killer problem, but it is something to be aware of.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">The real limitation on using pumped storage is the difficulty of finding a good place to have the two reservoirs. You need a high place for one reservoir and a low place for the other reservoir – and they have to be close together, like, within half a mile of each other. Most mountain ranges just aren't that steep: you won't find many big lakes that are really high and within half a mile of another big lake that's, say, a thousand feet lower.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">Fortunately, we can take advantage of fortuitous geography to create usable sites for pumped storage. The most common arrangement is to dig out a big reservoir on a hill or mountain above an existing lake or reservoir. Often dammed lakes or reservoirs are in mountainous terrain where there are plenty of good sites to build upper reservoirs. Still, digging out a complete reservoir from scrach can be an expensive proposition.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">Worldwide, we have a total of about 100 gigaWatts of pumped storage capacity; that's about as much as 100 individual big power plants can make. Europe leads the way with 37% of the total; Japan comes next with 25% of the total; and the USA comes in third with 20% of the total.</p><p style="font-size:110%"></p>]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pumped-storage_hydroelectricity">Wikipedia</a><br/>
		<a href="http://www.dom.com/about/stations/hydro/bath-county-pumped-storage-station.jsp">The largest pumped-storage facility in the USA</a><br/>
		<a href="http://www.renewableenergyworld.com/rea/news/article/2010/10/worldwide-pumped-storage-activity">A catalogue of pumped storage facilities under construction</a><br/>
		<br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/>
		<a href="http://lostontheshore.typepad.com/photos/uncategorized/2008/02/20/usace_kinzua_dam_downriver.jpg">Kinzua Dam facility</a><br/>]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="Rad Waste Disposal">
		<Text><![CDATA[<p style="font-size:110%">Some people think that we don't know how to store radioactive waste from nuclear power plants. This isn't true. The technology for radioactive waste disposal has been known for decades, and lots of engineering tests have been carried out to verify how well it works.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">The first step in the process is called <i>vitrification</i>, which just means "sealing it up inside glass". That doesn't mean putting it inside a glass bottle, it means actually mixing powdered radioactive waste into molten glass. We get thousands of little glass pellets, each one containing a small amount of radioactive waste inside. Fortunately, water doesn't dissolve glass, which is good, because otherwise you'd get water on your shirt every time you tried to drink some in a glass. In fact, almost nothing dissolves glass: sulfuric acid, nitric acid, nothing. Which means that, once the glass is buried, none of the radioactive stuff inside will dissolve into groundwater and then travel to the surface.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">Next, we put the glass pellets inside a big steel barrel. These steel barrels have been manufactured to withstand all sorts of damage without cracking. They're not indestructible, but you'd need something extremely powerful to crack open one of these babies.<p>
<p style="font-size:110%">Finally, we bury the barrels deep underground. There are about a dozen test facilities around the world where the stability of the surrounding rock is being investigated. There are also another dozen or so working repositories now under construction. The USA has an excellent site at Yucca Mountain in Nevada, which has undergone extensive testing and has been shown to be geologically ideal for long-term storage of radioactive waste. However, people living in Nevada don't like the idea of a nuclear waste repository in their state, no matter how safe, and have nixed the whole thing.<p>]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yucca_Mountain_nuclear_waste_repository">Wikipedia on Yucca Mountain Waste Repository</a><br/><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Radioactive_waste">Wikipedia on nuclear waste</a><br/><a href="http://www.world-nuclear.org/education/wast.htm">a pro-nuclear view</a><br/><a href="http://www.epa.gov/radiation/docs/radwaste/">US Environmental Protection Agency page on radioactive waste</a><br/><a href="http://www.ucsusa.org/assets/documents/nuclear_power/NPWWch5.pdf">an anti-nuclear view</a><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><a href="https://www-pls.llnl.gov/?url=science_and_technology-materials-yucca_mountain">tunnel diagram</a><br/><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/pnnl/3365376805/">vitrified pellets</a><br/>]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="Resources And Price">
		<Text><![CDATA[<p style="font-size:110%">In ancient times, you didn't have to dig for coal: you could find it lying around on the ground in the right places. Ancient peoples used tar, bitumen, and oil from oil seeps that come right up to the surface. But as the easy sources were used up, people started to dig deeper to get to the coal and oil. We've been doing that ever since, going further and deeper to get our resources.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">Obviously, the deeper you dig, and the more widely you explore, the more resource you'll get. But digging deeper and exploring further cost more money. This establishes a basic relationship between the supply of any resource and its price: the higher the price, the greater the supply.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">Thus, if we make a graph of the supply of a resource against its price, like the one shown here, we see curves that curve upwards, providing more and more energy at higher prices.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">But the curves for the fossil fuels only curve upwards at first; they're really bell-shaped curves. That's because there's only so much fossil fuel in the ground; eventually we'll reach the point where digging deeper doesn't produce much more fuel. We're already close to that point with oil; that point is called peak oil.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">Even the nonrenewable energy sources, such as solar energy, follow bell curves. After all, once we have completely covered the surface of the earth with solar panels, there won't be any more sunlight to harvest. But that day is so far away that it's reasonable to think that it will never come.</p>
		]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="Retrofits">
		<Text><![CDATA[<p style="font-size:110%">There's lots of energy waste around a typical home, and plenty of ways to decrease it. The starting place is heating and cooling. They cost energy, and the best way to reduce energy costs is to improve the <a href="Insulation">insulation</a> of your home.<br><a href="Windows">Windows</a> are another big source of heat loss.<br>Finally, <a href="Lighting">home lighting</a> is another area where you can make big savings in money and energy.</p>]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Energy_conservation">Wikipedia</a><br/><a href="http://www.energysavers.gov/tips/">some tips from the Feds</a><br/><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Homeowners-Handbook-Energy-Efficiency-Improvements/dp/1880120186/ref=sr_1_2?s=books&ie=UTF8&qid=1317498114&sr=1-2">a good book on how to save energy around the home</a>]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="Rich World People">
		<Text><![CDATA[<p style="font-size:110%">Two billion of the earth's population of seven billion enjoy a comfortable lifestyle. They have all the food they want – indeed, they suffer more from obesity than malnutrition. They have lots of clothes to wear, most of them have a car and a mobile phone. They watch television, go out the movies, surf the Internet, and play computer games.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">The average American uses about 300 gigaJoules every year. That's enough energy to put 5 tons of stuff into orbit around the earth. That's enough to drive an average American car twice around the globe. That's enough energy to run an incandescent 100 watt light bulb for a hundred years. Yep, we use a <b>lot</b> of energy.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">The average German uses only 176 gigaJoules; the average Chinese uses 47 gigaJoules, less than one-sixth what the average American uses. At the bottom end of the scale come countries like Bangladesh and Senegal, which use less than 10 gigaJoules per person per year. However, there are some countries that use more energy than we do: Bahrain and the United Arab Emirates, rich with oil and using lots of air-conditioning, use about 430 gigaJoules per person per year. The people in the freezing country of Iceland use 500 gigaJoules per year to heat their houses. And the world record, at 900 gigaJoules per year, is held by the tiny and fabulously wealthy country of Qatar.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">We gobble up a lot of other resources. Americans use more than 100 gallons of water per person each day; people in Mozambique use only about 5 gallons of water per person per day. Americans use more than 300 pounds of plastic per year; Africans use only 22. We eat 275 pounds of meat each year, but people in Bangladesh eat about 3 pounds per year. The list goes on and on, but the basic fact is simple: people in the Rich World use up most of the resources on this planet.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">We are also the biggest polluters. Americans emit about 18 tons of carbon dioxide per person each year; people in poor countries in Africa emit only about a hundred pounds of carbon dioxide per person per year.</p>]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Developed_country">Wikipedia</a><br/>
		<a href="http://www.amazon.com/How-Rich-Countries-Poor-Stay/dp/0786718420">a book on rich and poor countries</a><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/>
		<a href="http://www.me.ngb.army.mil/Family/Yellow%20Ribbon/Yellow%20Ribbon/YR%20media%20CD/Soldier-Family%20Images/happy%20family%203.jpg">rich world family</a><br/>]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="Solar Cells">
		<Text><![CDATA[<p style="font-size:110%">Solar cells are special pieces of silicon that convert sunlight into electricity. The electricity they produce is called <i>solar photovoltaic</i> energy, or just <i>solar PV</i> for short. Here's how they work:</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">We start with a happy-go-lucky photon from the sun (a photon is a <a href="Light">particle of light</a>) comes sailing down to the earth. The photon hits the solar cell and penetrates a short distance (a few millionths of an inch) into the cell. It eventually collides with an atom inside the solar cell, knocking loose an electron. This kind of thing happens all the time with all kinds of different substances. Normally, the electron wanders around for a little while and eventually finds its way back home. But the solar cell is made of special stuff that makes it impossible for the electron to get back home. That special stuff consists of two different kinds of silicon joined together. Where they meet, they form a barrier zone that an electron can pass through in one direction, but not the other way. It's kind of like a one-way turnstile: once you go in, you can't come back out.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">At the bottom of the solar cell is an aluminum plate that conducts electricity. When the electron hits that plate, it zips right through it, coming out of the solar cell in a wire. The electron wants so much to get home that it is willing to move through our circuits as electricity, doing useful things for us, in order to reach the wire that will take it back to the top of the solar cell, where it can travel back downward to get home.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">Some people think that this is cruel to electrons. What do you think?</p>]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Solar_cell">Wikipedia</a><br/>
		<a href="http://science.howstuffworks.com/environmental/energy/solar-cell.htm">another explanation</a><br/>
		<a href="http://www.scientificsonline.com/project-components/solar-cells-panels.html">some solar cell educational projects to buy</a><br/>]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="Solar Water Heating">
		<Text><![CDATA[<p style="font-size:110%">The simplest and most effective way to use solar energy is to use it to heat water. The technology has been available for decades, it works well and is reliable. All it takes is a big copper plate (painted black) inside an insulated box with a window, facing the sun. You weld some copper pipes to the big black copper plate, and then connect the pipes to a water tank above the solar panel. The sun heats up the black pipe, and the heat is transferred through the copper to the water in the pipes. That water becomes warmer and, because it's warmer, it rises in the pipes, moving into the water tank. The coolest water in the water tank flows downward into the bottom of the water pipes inside the solar panel. Thus, water slowly circulates through the system, getting hotter and hotter until it reaches its maximum temperature. When you want hot water, you turn on the tap and the hot water from the tank flows out your tap.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">People have been using solar water heating for a long time. Armies have used metal drums painted black as a quick and portable means to make warm water for showers. People have been selling solar water heating systems for homes since the 1970s. They really do work, they really do save money, and they really are reliable.</p>]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[<a href="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/d/db/Calefon_solar_termosifonico_compacto.jpg/800px-Calefon_solar_termosifonico_compacto.jpg">Solar water heater</a>]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="Spent Fuel Pools">
		<Text><![CDATA[<p style="font-size:110%">Like batteries, fuel rods don't last forever; after a while they lose most of their usable energy and they have to be replaced with fresh fuel rods. What do we do with the used-up fuel rods?</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">These things are <b>really</b> dangerous – they're full of extremely radioactive materials. This is what we call <i>radioactive waste</i> and it is imperative that it never, <b>ever</b> gets loose in the environment. To accomplish this, we need to build <a href="Rad Waste Disposal">long-term radioactive waste repositories</a>. However, we have a problem doing this: nobody wants a long-term radioactive waste disposal in their back yard. Whenever the government tries to set up a disposal site, the local people scream bloody murder and chase the government away. So we don't have any working radioactive waste disposal sites. Meanwhile, nuclear reactors all over the world are making lots and lots of radioactive waste. Where does it all go?</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">We leave them at the nuclear power plant, that's where. You see, when those used-up fuel rods come out of the reactor, they're so dangerously radioactive that it's not safe to ship them anywhere. Instead, we have a big concrete pool right next to the reactor, filled with water. We put the spent fuel rods into that pool. The water serves two purposes: first, it gobbles up all the radiation coming out of the fuel rods, so the workers are safe. Second, it cools the fuel rods, which continue to generate a lot of heat for months. After a few years, the fuel rods have cooled down enough for us to ship them to a safe place.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">But because there's no safe place to send them to, we just keep them where they are. Those pools were designed to hold only a few sets of fuel rods, temporarily, and for decades now, we've been stuffing <b>ALL</b> of the spent fuel rods into them, which really overloads the cooling systems.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">So we just keep postponing action and the most dangerous radioactive waste in the world stays inside pools of water, and we hope that nothing goes wrong. It didn't work at <a href="What Happened at Fukushima">Fukushima</a>.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">That spooky blue color in the photo is called <i>Cerenkov radiation</i>. It's just blue light, but physicists think it's really cool, because it happens when subatomic particles (electrons, protons, neutrons, that kind of thing) come screaming out of the spent fuel and enter the water. The speed of light in water is less than the speed of light in the fuel, so the subatomic particles have to give up some energy so that they can stay below the speed limit of the speed of light. The energy they give up is the blue light we call Cerenkov radiation. I haven't the faintest idea who Mr. Cerenkov was.</p>]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[<a href="https://radyananda.wordpress.com/2011/03/26/us-stores-spent-nuclear-fuel-rods-at-4-times-pool-capacity/">spent fuel pool</a><br/>]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="Stratospheric Sulfate">
		<Text><![CDATA[<p style="font-size:110%">Here's an idea: let's fly airplanes high up into the stratosphere where they dump tons and tons of sulfate compounds in a fine mist. Those compounds would form an aerosol that would slightly block sunlight. This would counter the greenhouse effect created by all the carbon dioxide we release. Injecting a million tons of such sulfates each year should be sufficient to cancel out the effects of the carbon dioxide we emit every year.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">They calculate that this would cost maybe $50 billion per year. Since climate change could end up costing us maybe as much as a trillion dollars per year, this really does sound like a bargain.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">But there is a catch (first rule of environmental problems: there's <u>always</u> a catch). In this case, the catch is that we don't know what the side effects would be. There's a chance that it could lead to nasty droughts in some places; if that happens, could the victims of the drought sue the people spraying the sulfates for a few billion bucks? Also, there's a chance that this would lead to ozone depletion, which would damage agriculture and cause more cases of skin cancer (but only among light-skinned people).</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">This option is a huge gamble. It just might work. Or it just might create even worse problems. Are you feeling lucky today, punk?</p>]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stratospheric_sulfur_aerosols_(geoengineering)">Wikipedia</a><br/><a href="http://ocw.mit.edu/courses/civil-and-environmental-engineering/1-018j-ecology-i-the-earth-system-fall-2009/projects/MIT1_018JF09_sw_paper4.pdf">possible unintended consequences</a><br/><a href="http://gokill.com/2010/05/15/stratospheric-sulfate-aerosols-geoengineering/">another point of view</a><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><a href="http://jazzroc.files.wordpress.com/2008/10/strat.jpg?w=516&h=225">airplane</a><br/>]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="Strip Mining">
		<Text><![CDATA[<p style="font-size:110%">The safest and most efficient way to dig coal, if it's not too deep, is to remove the soil over it and then just shovel it up. The machine that shovels up the coal is called a <i>dragline</i>, and the biggest one in the world is the <a href="Bagger 288">Bagger 288</a>, capable of digging up enough coal in one day to fill 2,400 railroad cars. This kind of mechanization has made strip mining very efficient.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">In the USA, strip mining is practiced in a great many states, with some of the biggest operations being in Wyoming and neighboring states, and West Virginia and its neighboring states. The photograph shows a strip mine in Wyoming.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">The most controversial form of strip mining involves <i>mountain top removal</i>. West Virginia is hilly (well, Easterners would call it "mountainous"), and many of those mountains have a thick layer of coal a hundred feet or more down from the top. So they use bulldozers to push the dirt off the top of the mountain, leaving just the coal layer, which they then scoop up.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">When they're done, they have to fix the mess they made. They bulldoze a lot of dirt back and smooth everything out into a flat area where once there was a big hill (or small mountain, if you're an Easterner). They then pack everything down, put soil on top, and plant and water grass on the new flat spot they made.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">Advocates of this kind of mining argue that they restore the land environmentally, and they convert useless hills ("mountains!") into usable land. They point out that these new lands have been put to all sorts of uses: golf courses, local airports, and trailer parks, among other things. Such uses would have been impossible beforehand, they argue.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">Opponents point out that mountain top removal generates millions of tons of loose rock and dirt that are piled into local valleys, contaminating  the local streams. Although the mining companies plant grass on the new land, trees don't grow well in the poor soil, so you end up replacing a tree-covered hill ("MOUNTAIN!!!") with a grassy flat-top.</p>]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Strip_mining#Strip_mining">Wikipedia</a><br/>
		<a href="http://www.citizenscoalcouncil.org/index.php?option=com_content&view=article&id=13&Itemid=21">an "anti" website with a lot of explanatory material</a><br/>
		<a href="http://eobadmin.gsfc.nasa.gov/Features/MountaintopRemoval/">an even-handed website from NASA</a><br/>
		<a href="http://www.coaleducation.org/">a "pro" educational website</a><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/>		
		<a href="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/0/05/">strip mine</a><br/>]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="The Grid">
		<Text><![CDATA[<p style="font-size:110%">Electricity is manufactured in power plants, and then brought to your home by big wires. Sounds pretty simple, right? Well, it isn't. There are a jillion factors that make it difficult to connect your house to the power plant. The first is the fact that some of the <a href="Transmission Losses">electricity is lost</a> moving down the wires. Second, the amount of energy that people want <a href="Variable Demand">changes through the day</a>. Third, people in <a href="Different Volts for Different Folks">different areas</a> want different amounts of electricity, and different power plants are in different places. And fourth, <a ref="Power Plant Regularity">different kinds of power plants</a> produce electricity in differing amounts at different times. See: 1, 2, 3, a jillion. What'd I tell you?</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">
		The map shows the electrical grid for the United States. It shows all the power lines carrying power from one place to another. As you can see, it's quite complicated: we need a lot of transmission lines in the east, where there are lots of people crowded together. There aren't that many people in the mountain states, so there isn't much need for power and not so many power lines. The people crowded along the West Coast use of lots of power, and so they need a dense network of power lines.]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="The Technological Fix">
		<Text><![CDATA[<p style="font-size:110%">A hundred years ago, most short-haul transportation was powered by horses. Inside cities, thousands of horses pulled freight, buses, and taxis. New York City had 100,000 horses using its streets, depositing 2.5 million pounds of manure on its streets every day. A huge force of street cleaners was required to keep the streets passable. Every year, the increasing number of people and goods moving through the city required more and more horses; a mountain of horse shit threatened to bury New York City. Hands were wrung; eyebrows were furrowed; nobody could conceive a solution to the problem.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">Twenty years later, the problem was all but solved. The internal combustion engine had allowed trucks and automobiles to replace horses. Cars, unlike horses, don't leave shit on the ground (but they do fart pollution into the air, a problem that grew as more and more cars were used).</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">Fifty years ago, the world seemed doomed to starvation. Three billion mouths had to be fed, yet the food supply wasn't keeping up with human fertility. Experts warned that starvation on such a scale would lead to civil wars, rebellions, insurgencies, and even international wars. They called it "The Population Bomb". But how could disaster be averted? The world's farms were already running at full steam; there wasn't any new land to open up for new farms.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">Fifty years later, we have seven billion mouths, and while malnutrition remains a serious problem, we have increased agricultural productivity so much that we really could feed everybody if only we had better distribution systems for food. This was made possible by the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Green_Revolution">Green Revolution</a>. By developing higher-yield crops, crops that could grow with less water, and improved fertilizers, herbicides, and pesticides, scientists were able to dramatically increase agricultural productivity and defuse the Population Bomb.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">The history of the last century sparkles with stories like these: seemingly intractable problems solved by the wonders of modern science. It's almost like a fairy tale: the Evil Monster is just about to devour the Fair Maiden when Super-Scientist arrives to save the day. We've seen this story play out so many times that we've started to take it for granted. All over the world, Fair Maidens are checking their watches and tapping their feet, wondering aloud, is that damn Super-Scientist going to take all day to get here?</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">Some people go so far that they don't see much need to worry about problems like energy or climate change or pollution; they figure that science will surely solve the problem for us someday. This attitude is called <b>The Technological Fix</b>: for every problem, there's a technological fix. "What, me worry?" they say; "The scientists will surely fix it any day now."</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">And, most of the time, they're right! Yep, science has saved our butts over and over again. But the fact that science can solve <u>most</u> of our problems doesn't mean that it can solve <u>all</u> of our problems. There are plenty of problems that science hasn't been able to solve.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">For example, take traffic congestion. For the last fifty years, commuters have had to sit in traffic jams for hours on end, crawling inch by inch to get where they're going. We build new freeways, bigger freeways, add more ramps and special traffic control systems – and we're still getting there no faster than we were fifty years ago. All the super-duper science and technology in the world has accomplished very little when it comes to traffic congestion.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">Or how about fusion energy? Fifty years ago, we were sure that someday soon, we'd have nuclear reactors using fusion energy. They'd use the hydrogen in plain water as fuel, and there's enough water on this planet to keep us rolling in fusion energy for millions of years. Electricity would be so cheap and plentiful, we'd never have to worry about energy again. Well, fifty years have passed and we STILL don't have a working fusion reactor, and we're not even close.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">The list of problems that science has failed to solve is long: we haven't found a cure for cancer, or even the common cold. We still don't have cars that fly, and we still can't talk to computers in plain English (although we're starting to get close with technologies like Siri). Solar cells are getting cheaper every day, but back in 1975 we were sure they'd be dirt cheap within twenty years. Despite all of our grand technological advances, our main source of electricity all over the world comes from burning old-fashioned, low-tech coal. Electric cars have been around for a hundred years, but we still don't have an affordable electric car with acceptable performance (although again, we're starting to get close).</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">The moral of this story is simple: Super-Scientist does a good job, and he often shows up in the nick of time to save Fair Maiden, but she'd be a fool to get herself into precarious situations expecting Super-Scientist to swoop down and save her every time. Sometimes, Super-Scientist is busy saving somebody else's goose; sometimes, he's sitting on the toilet; and sometimes, his super-powers just aren't enough to save the day.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%"></p>
		<p style="font-size:110%"></p>]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Techno-Fix-Technology-Wont-Save-Environment/dp/0865717044/ref=sr_1_2?s=books&ie=UTF8&qid=1324188075&sr=1-2">a book on the problems with the technological fix</a><br/>
		<a href="http://mitpress.mit.edu/books/chapters/0262072823chap1.pdf">a chapter from a book about the problems of the technological fix</a><br/>
		<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Technological-Fix-Technology-Problems-Perspectives/dp/0415947111">another book on the technological fix.</a><br/>]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="Thermal Equilibrium">
		<Text><![CDATA[<p style="font-size:110%"><i>Equilibrium</i> is just the snotty word for "balance", so thermal equilibrium is a situation where all the heat is in balance. For example, consider the earth. We've got sunlight pouring in – about 200 petaWatts worth of heat power hitting the earth. That warms the earth. But, remember, the earth has heat, and so it emits infrared radiation. How much does it emit? Normally, it emits exactly the same amount of energy in the form of infrared light out into space. How can we know that? Because the earth is (almost) in equilibrium. The amount of heat going out has to equal the amount of heat coming in. Otherwise, the temperature of the earth would change.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">Here's an example: suppose that the sun were suddenly to get twice as bright, so that it was sending us not 200 petaWatts of heat power, but <b>400</b> petaWatts of heat power. All that extra heat would cause the earth to start getting hotter, right? The temperature would go up. But here's the trick: remember how (in the page about <a href="Thermal Radiation">Thermal Radiation</a>) I told you that the hotter an object is, the more radiation it emits (and the bluer that radiation is)? If the earth were to heat up because of all that extra sunlight, its temperature would rise and it would therefore emit more infrared radiation. As long as there was more sunlight energy coming in than infrared energy going out, the earth's temperature would continue to rise. But eventually it has to rise far enough that the amount of infrared radiation going out is equal to the amount of sunlight energy coming in. At that point, the earth will be back in thermal equilibrium and temperatures will remain constant.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">It works the other way around, too. Suppose that the sun were to suddenly get only half as bright as it is now, so that instead of 200 petawatts of sunlight coming in, we had only 100 petawatts of sunlight coming in. The earth would still be radiating 200 petawatts, so there would be more infrared energy leaving the earth than sunlight coming in. But if the earth is losing heat energy into space, then its total heat content goes down: in other words, it cools. Its temperature goes down, which means that it emits less than 200 petawatts. So long as the amount of infrared radiation that it emits is greater than the amount of sunlight coming in, the earth will continue to cool until it reaches a new thermal balance – oops, thermal <u>equilibrium</u></p>
<p style="font-size:110%">Thus, the earth automatically adjusts its temperature to stay in balance with the sunlight coming in – and it does it all without a single computer!<p>
<p style="font-size:110%">But this is only the beginning of the story. It's what we call a <i>first approximation</i>: a short, simple version of the truth, that leaves out messy details so that you can understand it. Now we're going to start throwing in messy details. The first messy detail is <a href="Absorption">absorption</a>.</p>]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="Thermal Power Plant">
		<Text><![CDATA[<p style="font-size:110%">Most big power plants (coal, oil, nuclear, and natural gas) operate by using the fuel as a source of heat. The heat boils water into steam. Now, when water boils into steam, it expands to 1700 times its original volume, and if we keep it bottled up inside pipes, that increases the pressure inside the pipes. We run the pipes into a <a href="Turbine">turbine</a>, and the steam makes the turbine spin. The turbine is connected to a generator, which makes electricity. Then wires take the electricity right here into your computer. Just think: the electricity within a fraction of an inch of your fingertips is coming from a bunch of superheated steam far away.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">But we're not done yet. After it leaves the turbine, it goes into a <a href="Condenser">condenser</a>, which turns it back into water. Then we pump it right back into the boiler to repeat the cycle.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">The condenser is able to cool the steam and condense it back into water because it has a steady supply of cool water provided by <a href="Hyperbolic Cooling Towers">hyperbolic cooling towers</a> which cool tremendous amounts of water without a single moving part.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">And that's how power plants work.</p>]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="Thermal Radiation">
		<Text><![CDATA[<p style="font-size:110%"><i>Thermal Radiation</i>: sounds pretty scary, right? Like, maybe, radioactive monsters that are hot, or something like that, right? Well, no, it's actually nowhere near as much fun as that; in fact, thermal radiation is a common, everyday thing that you already know about, you just haven't heard the snazzy name that makes you sound like you're smart when you use it.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">Anything that has any heat in it at all will radiate thermal radiation. You can feel that thermal radiation on your face when you stand close to a fire. The hotter the fire, the more thermal radiation you feel. But high temperature does more than make <b>more</b> thermal radiation – it makes <b>bluer</b> thermal radiation. In other words, as the temperature of something gets higher, its color becomes bluer. If you have an electric stovetop, you can see this happening: turn on the stove to its highest temperate and watch closely. The first you'll see is a dark red color on the coils; then the color will become brighter and more like normal red. As it gets really hot, it starts to look orange. If you had a turbo-charged stovetop, then you could raise the temperature even higher and the coils would become yellow-hot, then blue-hot. However, that temperature would be so high that the stove would melt and you'd burn your house down. And by the way, if you do perform this experiment, please do not sit down on the stove, lick the coils, touch them with your hand, or other such idiocy. Yes, there really are people stupid enough to try things like that!</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">Because the earth has heat, it also emits thermal radiation. Fortunately, you don't have to be careful when walking on the earth's surface ("Ouch! Ouch! The thermal radiation is getting me!"), because that thermal radiation takes the form of infrared radiation, which our eyes cannot see. (If you think about it, it's a good thing that we can't see infrared radiation; if we could, then everywhere we looked, we'd see thermal radiation and the whole world would look like a brightly lit pure white room.) So the earth is constantly emitting infrared light out into space. It's all part of the process called <a href="Thermal Equilibrium">thermal equilibrium</a>.</p>]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[<a href="http://images.fastcompany.com/upload/natural_gas_set_to_change_everything_about_fight_for_energy_independence-720907.jpg">gas burner</a><br/><a href="link">label</a><br/><a href="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/3/36/Large_bonfire.jpg">bonfire</a><br/><a href="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/1/1e/Embers_01.JPG">embers</a>]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="Tiny Cars">
		<Text><![CDATA[<p style="font-size:110%">America is the only country in the world where you don't see many tiny cars; Americans regard such cars with derision. It's a shame, because these little cars are great ways to get around. The car shown in the picture is called a "SmartCar". It's a two-seater that gets about 40 mpg and costs around $14,000. This car is no slouch, either – it has a top speed of around 90 mph, and it can easily maintain 65 mph fully loaded.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">Little cars like this swarm all over European, Latin American, and Asian roads; the total number of such cars might be as high as 100 million. They're popular because they're so practical. They all get great gas mileage, they carry two people plus some spare space for groceries, they're quick, and they're easy to park. All in all, little cars are better for many people the world over.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">Few Americans realize just how expensive their cars are. The average cost of owning a car in the US is about $8,000 per year. Of that, roughly $2,000 goes to gasoline. Moreover, big cars cost more and depreciate faster. When you add up all the costs, a small car costs about $2000 per year less than a big car.</p?
<p style="font-size:110%">So why don't Americans like them? American culture puts the automobile on a pedestal. Big, powerful, fast cars are idolized. A lot of American men think that their car reflects their manhood: real men drive big cars. Does the size of one's bicycle reflect your manhood? Does the size of your handkerchief say "I'm a REAL man"?</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">Bigger is not necessarily better; it's just bigger. In the case of cars, bigger usually means faster and more powerful, but it also means more expensive to purchase, more expensive to operate, and harder to park.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">I have a really big hat that I sometimes wear. One day I got into an elevator and this other fellow strode in wearing a cowboy hat. The elevator doors closed and we started moving. There was dead silence as we rode up. Just before the doors opened at my floor, I turned to the other guy and said, "Mah hat is BIGGER than yore hat!" Then I got off the elevator.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">Is yore car bigger than the other guy's?</p>]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[<a href="http://www.grinzo.com/energy/">cost of operating a car</a><br/>
		<a href="http://www.smartusa.com/">SmartCar website</a><br/>
		<a href="http://www.cnbc.com/id/42798040/Coolest_Small_Cars">some cool small cars</a><br/>
		<br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/>Images:<a href="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/6/6f/Smart.car.bristol.750pix.jpg">SmartCar</a><br/>]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="Transmission Losses">
		<Text><![CDATA[<p style="font-size:110%">All you need to carry electricity is a wire, but, as with everything on this sad planet that clouds our sunny days, there's a catch: some of the electricity is lost in transmission down the wire. When electricity travels through wires, it heats them slightly, reducing the amount of electricity that comes out the other end of the wire. If it's a LOT of electricity and a LITTLE wire, then the wire can actually melt.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">When I was a kid, I used to take apart little electric motors and unwind the fine wire inside, then stick both ends of the wire into the electrical outlet. The wire would turn bright red and vaporize – what fun! (We didn't have videogames back then.) Anyway, if you try to do this yourself, you're a drooling idiot, just like I was. I did all sorts of idiotic things when I was a kid. I will never understand how I survived my childhood.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">
		Anyway, getting back to electricity transmission: the most effective technique to reduce transmission losses is to use higher voltages, which lose less energy to heat. For many years, power transmission lines have used voltages of 200,000 volts and higher. But higher voltages are trickier to work with, and so most transmission lines use something between 200,000 and 500,000 volts.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">
		Even so, we lose about 6% of all the electricity we produce to transmission losses. That lost electricity is worth about $30 billion every year. Obviously, anything we can do to reduce that loss will save us a lot of money. One of the best ways to do this is with <a href="High Voltage Direct Current">HVDC: High Voltage DC lines.</a></p>]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Electric_power_transmission">Wikipedia</a><br/>
		<a href="http://psc.wi.gov/thelibrary/publications/electric/electric09.pdf">more than you could possibly want to know about transmission lines</a><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><a href="http://mendocoastcurrent.wordpress.com/2010/03/01/utilities-push-back-on-fercs-transmission-authority/">transmission lines</a><br/>]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="Turbine">
		<Text><![CDATA[<p style="font-size:110%">Take a child's pinwheel, as shown in the upper left. Blow on it, and it spins. Now scale things up: instead of blowing air out of your mouth, direct a blast of superheated steam at it. It spins <b>really</b> fast before disintegrating, doesn't it? OK, so let's make it bigger and stronger, like the monster steel thing in the upper right. That could easily handle the steam, couldn't it? And it would turn <b>really</b> fast, right? This is what we call a <i>turbine</i> A turbine converts the energy of high-pressure steam into spinning energy. That's all it does. This kind of turbine is used in power plants that burn coal, oil, or natural gas; in nuclear power plants, geothermal plants, and solar thermal plants.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">But turbines can also work in the other direction, converting spinning energy into air motion. When they operate like this, we call them fans. The biggest and most powerful of these are turbofan jet engines, like the one in the bottom of the picture.</p>]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Turbine">Wikipedia</a><br/>
		<br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><a href="http://connect.in.com/steam-turbine/photos-large-steam-turbine-jpg-35560cbb64670754.html">turbine</a><br/>
		<a href="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/3/35/British_Airways_B757_Heathrow_Airport_jet_engine_intake.jpg/800px-British_Airways_B757_Heathrow_Airport_jet_engine_intake.jpg">jet engine</a>]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="Underground Mining">
		<Text><![CDATA[<p style="font-size:110%">Some coal is so deep underground that the only way to reach it is to dig a deep mine. Once you get to the coal, it's pretty easy to mine, because coal is soft. Machines with big teeth cut into the coal, which falls onto a conveyor belt that takes it up to the surface. Long gone are the days when miners swung pickaxes.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">Underground mining used to be extremely dangerous. Over 100,000 coal miners were killed in mining accidents in the USA during the 20th century. However, with proper safety precautions, mining can be made much safer. Nowadays only a few dozen miners are killed in the USA every year. However, there is a more insidious killer of coal miners: lung disease, which strikes 4% of American coal miners every year. Although it is not necessarily fatal, it always shortens a person's lifespan.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">In other countries without strict safety requirements, however, underground coal mining kills many more people. In China, by far the world's largest producer of coal, perhaps 10,000 miners die each year.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">Underground coal mining has only one significant environmental impact: subsidence. After the miners have finished mining all the coal in a section, they permit it to collapse onto itself; this is done for safety purposes. All the rock over the section shifts downward, and the surface drops as well. With a big mine, this leaves a large, shallow depression in the ground. This depression prevents water from draining away properly. Compared to surface mining, this is small beans.</p>]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Coal_mining">Wikipedia</a><br/>
		<a href="http://www.umwa.org/?q=content/underground-coal-mining">mine workers' union</a><br/>
		<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Coal-Human-History-Barbara-Freese/dp/0142000981/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&ie=UTF8&qid=1317402220&sr=1-1">A great book on coal mining in the bad old days</a><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><a href="http://princetonwvonline.com/images/coalmine006.jpg">coal shearer</a>]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="Variable Demand">
		<Text><![CDATA[<p style="font-size:110%">Twas one in the morning, and all through the house, not a machine was running, except for maybe the refrigerator, and the alarm clock, and the computer, and the cellphone charger, and some other things. But when the people woke up, they turned on lights, ran the coffeemaker, and used more electricity. In the afternoon, it got hot, so they turned on the air conditioning, using a LOT more electricity. When evening came, they used the oven to make dinner, watched TV, played videogames, and did a bunch of other things needing electricity. But as evening turned to night, they started going to bed, and they used less and less electricity.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">
		Now multiply this by a million families in a million homes, and imagine that you're the guy running the power plant who has to provide all the electricity. During the night, you don't want to generate much electricity: if you do make too much electricity, the voltage will get too high and people's TVs, computers, microwave ovens, and videogames will burn out, and the videogamers will come and get you. So you have to make only a little electricity in the middle of the night.</br>
		But when morning comes, you want to start increasing the amount of electricity you generate, and steadily increasing it all through the day. Normally, you'll have to make the most electricity in the late afternoon, but it depends alot on the season and location.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">
		Big deal, you say: he just has to turn the volume dial on his power plant, turning it up or down as needed. Sorry, power plants don't work that way. <a href="Power Plant Regularity">Different kinds of power plants</a> operate differently and have to be carefully managed.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">
		This variation in demand for electricity creates one of the nastiest problems with electricity: the difference between <i>peak load</i> and <i>base load</i>. That difference is the cause of <a href="Peak Load Versus Base Load">additional costs</a>.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">
		There are about 500 grids in the US, most of them are connected together in a single super-grid. Each separate grid has its own control room with grid operators who constantly monitor the flow of power through the grid. They handle changes by turning on and off their hydroelectric or natural gas power plants (if they have any). They also buy or sell power with other grids. Every control room is protected against terrorists and has a big supply of antacid pills.</p>]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="Walking">
		<Text><![CDATA[<p style="font-size:110%">The average American walks about 2.5 miles per day. By contrast, people in Australia and Switzerland walk about 5 miles per day, and Japanese walk about 3.5 miles per day. Amish people, who don't drive cars, walk an average of 8 miles per day. Doctors recommend about 5 miles of walking per day as a good rule of thumb for healthy living. This is one reason why so many Americans are obese: they just don't get enough exercise. So, the best reason to walk more is for your own health.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">But walking instead of driving also saves energy, especially for short trips. When a car is first started and is still warming up, it doesn't get as good mileage as when it's fully warmed up.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">Moreover, what with all the time spent dealing with the particular delays of automobile travel (getting in the car, starting it up, backing it out, waiting for traffic, finding a parking place, and so on), the speed advantage of a car is cancelled out for short trips. How long should a trip be in order to justify taking the car instead of walking? The answer, of course, depends upon your own tastes. I live up in the mountains, and my mailbox is half a mile away from my house. I never take the car to get the mail; I always walk. My nearest neighbor is about 3/4 of a mile away from my house; I usually drive to get there, although on nice days I'll sometimes take the shorter walking route through the woods.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">Lastly, there's the most important reason to walk instead of drive: it's just a lot more pleasant.</p>]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[<a href="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/walking/HQ01612">The Mayo Clinic on the health benefits of walking</a><br/>
		<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Walking-Complete-Guide-Exercise/dp/0345491041/ref=sr_1_3?s=books&ie=UTF8&qid=1317440955&sr=1-3">a book on walking</a> "First, put your left foot forward..."<br/>
		<a href="http://www.transcendentalists.com/walking.htm">Henry David Thoreau on walking</a><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/>
		<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:KeepOnTruckin%27.jpg">Keep On Truckin'</a><br/><br/>]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="Water Turbine">
		<Text><![CDATA[<p style="font-size:110%">A water turbine converts the energy of moving water into spinning energy. Water turbines are used inside hydroelectric dams to turn generators that make electricity. They're huge, so that they can handle enormous amounts of water.</p>
		<p style="font-size:110%">Just like regular <a href="Turbine">turbines</a>, water turbines work in both directions: they can convert spinning energy into the motion of water. So if you hook up a water turbine to an engine and turn it, it will push water. Only then you call it a propellor, like in the picture on the lower left.</p>]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[<br><br><br><br><br><br><br><br><a href="http://www.theroadscholar.net/images/May%202009/kentucky%20Dam%20Turbine%2003.jpg">water turbine</a><br/><a href="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/3/35/Ship-propeller.jpg">propellor</a><br/>]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="What Happened at Fukushima">
		<Text><![CDATA[<p style="font-size:110%">On March 11th, 2011, an earthquake struck 60 miles off the coast of Japan. This earthquake, at magnitude 9.0, was the largest earthquake in Japanese history and one of the largest in human history. The nuclear reactors in Japan all weathered the quake well and shut down safely. So far, so good.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">But then came the tsunami. When the plant was built, the government had estimated that the largest possible tsunami that could ever hit the plant was 19 feet high, and so the plant had seawalls high enough to stop such a tsunami. But the tsunami that hit was actually 46 feet high. The water went right over the seawalls and into the plant area, flooding everything. Powerlines to the plant were all knocked out. All the diesel emergency generators that were designed to provide emergency power in case outside power was lost were inundated and rendered inoperable by the seawater. There were two emergency diesel generators at a higher elevation, but their wiring ran though the basement of the reactors and was flooded. The electrical pumps that supplied cooling water to the reactors were also flooded and ruined.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">The plant was also equipped with huge batteries that kept vital systems running for three hours, but by the time the batteries ran out of juice, there was still no external power. Long stretches of power lines to the plant had been destroyed; even the roads leading to the plant were damaged or clogged with debris. Help wasn't able to arrive anytime soon.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">The reactors had all been shut down safely but the decay heat still required large amounts of cooling water. There were no working pumps to supply that water, so the reactor cores steadily grew hotter and hotter. Eventually, three of the six reactor cores partially melted down.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">But the fun had just started. When a reactor overheats, a chemical reaction between the cooling water and the fuel rods generates lots of free hydrogen gas. That hydrogen gas seeped out of the <i>primary containment structure</i>, a huge concrete and steel box that is supposed to keep everything inside even in a bad accident. The hydrogen gas collected in the upper portion of the <i>secondary containment structure</i>, which is actually pretty flimsy. Eventually something – a spark perhaps, or maybe a superheated piece of metal – ignited the hydrogen, and there was a big explosion, shown in the photograph. This was not a nuclear explosion, but it was big enough to shatter the secondary containment structure.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">This did NOT release the radioactive materials inside the core of the reactor. Those materials are inside a huge steel vessel, and we believe that all three vessels pretty much held through the explosion. When the reactors did partially melt hours later, the pressure vessels succeeded in holding most of the molten radioactive stuff inside, but we believe that some of the liquid mess dropped down into the bottom the containment building. This stuff is intensely radioactive and very hot; if it had been blown out of the containment building there would have been enormous amounts of radioactivity released. It appears that this did not happen; most of what escaped was gaseous.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">But it got even worse. Once the electricity to the power plant was lost, there were no pumps to keep pumping more cooling water into the <a href="Spent Fuel Pools">spent fuel pools</a>. The water got hotter and hotter, and after a few days, all the water had boiled away. Without cooling water, the old fuel rods started to get really hot, and eventually they caught fire. The smoke from that fire was extremely radioactive, and the wind carried that smoke away from the power plant. Luckily for us, most of the smoke blew out to sea, but some of it went over parts of Japan, dropping radioactive contamination. The smoke from the burning fuel rods in the spent fuel pools was probably the biggest source of release of radioactivity.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">They've been measuring the radioactivity in various parts of Japan and it looks as if the worst radioactivity was kept pretty close to the plant. The safety evacuation zone, covering everything within 12 miles of the plant, will probably remain uninhabitable for at least five years. We're still gathering data, so none of this is certain.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">Does the Fukushima accident prove that nuclear power plants are unsafe? It's not reasonable to extrapolate from the Fukushima plants to the hundreds of other nuclear plants around the world, but a few lessons do emerge: 1) the reactors were able to function properly through an earthquake much more powerful than anybody ever expected; 2) they were not able to function properly when hit with a 46-foot high tsunami; 3) the backup systems that are supposed to handle even worst-case situations were not able to prevent a serious release of radioactivity. If you're pro-nuclear, you can argue that nuclear power plants that are not vulnerable to 46-foot high tsunamis are still safe. If you're anti-nuclear, you can argue that the back-up safety systems were not good enough to handle an unexpected event. And if you're in the middle, the only conclusion you can draw is that nuclear power plants can indeed be dangerous in extremely unlikely situations.</p>]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fukushima_Daiichi_nuclear_disaster">Wikipedia</a><br/>
		<a href="http://www.iaea.org/newscenter/focus/fukushima/index.html">The International Atomic Energy Agency reports on Fukushima</a><br/>
		<a href="http://www.world-nuclear.org/info/fukushima_accident_inf129.html">A nuclear industry group gives its side of the story</a><br/>
		<a href="http://www.who.int/mediacentre/news/releases/2013/fukushima_report_20130228/en/index.html">The World Health Organization report on health impact of Fukushima</a><br>
		<br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/>
		<a href="http://isrovation.files.wordpress.com/2011/03/fukushima_01.jpg">Fukushima explosion</a><br/>]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
	<Term Title="Windows">
		<Text><![CDATA[<p style="font-size:110%">The picture on the right is an infrared photograph of a house on a cold night. The red areas are hotspots where heat is escaping from the house; green and blue are cooler areas where little heat is escaping. Notice how most of the heat is escaping through the windows. Most of your heating bill (and your cooling bill, too!) goes to transmit heat through your windows into the great outdoors.</p>
<p style="font-size:110%">If you live in a cold area, your windows should be double-glazed (have two panes of glass instead of just one, with an air space between them). Even better, install some sort of window covering: drapes, curtains, or some other fabric that keeps the air close to the window from mixing with the air in the house. This is especially important if you have a central air heating system with an air vent that blows air right over the window. That is meant to prevent water condensation on the window, but drapes do a better job and don't waste energy.<br>Another place to look: are there air leaks at doors and windows? It's easy to check: when it's cold outside, run your fingers along the edges of every outside door and window. If you can feel a cold draft, then you need to replace the weatherstripping along that door or window. Hardware stores sell all sorts of different weatherstripping products, so many that you'll probably be confused. Ask for help.</p>]]></Text>
		<ReferenceText><![CDATA[<a href="http://www.nfrc.org/documents/U-Factor.pdf">An industry PDF about heat loss through windows</a><br/>
		<a href="http://www.builditsolar.com/References/Calculators/HeatLoss/HeatLoss.htm">a heat loss calculator that you can use for your own home</a><br/>
		<a href="http://homerepair.about.com/gi/dynamic/offsite.htm?zi=1/XJ/Ya&sdn=homerepair&cdn=homegarden&tm=7&gps=90_1951_1020_598&f=02&tt=14&bt=0&bts=0&zu=http%3A//www.eere.energy.gov/consumer/your_home/energy_audits/index.cfm/mytopic%3D11170">a do-it-yourself energy audit for your home</a><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/>
		<a href="http://bazaarhdc.files.wordpress.com/2010/01/architella_2.jpg">infrared house</a><br/>]]></ReferenceText>
	</Term>
</Backgrounders>
